Ok.
Dale.
Igual no hay sala de espera, así que van a
ir entrando.
Hola, hola.
¿Se escucha mejor?
¿Mejor ahí?
¿Ok?
It's better with the... this... in the
middle, yes.
Hari Om.
Sound test.
Can you hear me ok?
We record it in the cloud and then...
That's a good idea.
Because we have free space.
Ok, cool.
Yeah.
Thanks.
We can start whenever.
Hari Om Tat Sat.
Welcome to everyone.
We are going to go ahead and start.
Bienvenidos a todos.
Vamos a ir hacia adelante y comenzar.
My name is Sachidananda.
Can everyone hear me clearly?
Mi nombre es Sachidananda y está
preguntando si todos pueden oírlo con
claridad.
Y a mí también me dicen.
Great.
We will do Shantipat in a moment.
But before I just want to say a few words.
Vamos a empezar con Shantipat en un
momento.
Pero antes quiero decir una palabra.
And it's to make clear that I'm not a
doctor or a psychologist.
Es para dejar en claro que no soy un
doctor o un psicólogo.
I'm in no way certified as a healthcare
practitioner.
I'm also not an official representative of
the ashram or any school.
I have been studying under the Satyananda
Yoga tradition for many years.
And yoga in general for almost double that
time.
And so everything I share tonight is based
on life experiences.
Entonces todo lo que les voy a estar
compartiendo hoy está basado en
experiencias de vida.
Y mis experiencias no tienen que ser
tomadas como una guía de lo que puede ser
la experiencia para ustedes o de lo que
ustedes hayan experimentado.
Esta es una invitación para que ustedes
usen su discernimiento y su conciencia.
En cuanto a las técnicas que yo puedo
sugerir que ustedes prueben.
Or any idea that I present as good or
insightful.
Please run it through your own filters and
your own common sense if it's good for
you.
It's important for me to say that because
my concentration may be in other areas
than watching or considering each and
every person in the room.
We'll go ahead and now start with a formal
Shantipa.
Vamos a ir hacia adelante y comenzar con
el Shantipa.
Por favor, tómense un tiempo para
colocarse en una postura cómoda.
Pueden usar la asistencia de almohadones,
pillas.
Tomando un asana que puedan mantener por
tres a cinco minutos.
Of course, you're welcome to move as
needed, but there is value in coming to
stillness.
Obviamente están invitados a moverse si lo
necesitan, pero es una invitación a la
quietud, a mantenerla.
Continue to arrange your body so that the
spine is comfortably upright.
The shoulders and arms in a relaxed
position.
With the hands in a mudra or gesture of
your choice.
A simple one is to touch the tip of the
thumb to the first index finger.
With the palms up or down.
Resting on the knees or thighs.
The neck and head in alignment with the
lower spine.
Bring your awareness into your whole body
and really feel for the balance between
left and right sides.
Trae tu atención a todo el cuerpo y busca
el equilibrio entre tu lado derecho y tu
lado izquierdo.
Sentí esto en los pies, rodillas,
en los espiones.
Feel for that balance in the torso,
the shoulders, the neck and head.
Make any subtle adjustments to bring
yourself closer to physical balance if
required.
Y puedes hacer los ajustes necesarios para
traerte más cerca del equilibrio entre
ambos lados.
Once you have found some stillness,
start to focus on the movement of the
breath.
Una vez que hayas alcanzado cierta
quietud, focalizate en el movimiento de la
respiración.
Without changing it by force, just read
it, the quality of it at this time of the
day.
If it in any way reflects the activities
of the day.
And if any impressions of the day are
moving through the mind or the emotions.
Consider neither feeding them nor
resisting them.
Letting them move through you like clouds
and preferring to focus on the breath.
Begin to deepen the breath in both
directions gradually, progressively.
So that over a number of breaths,
you find that you are exhaling more
completely and inhaling more fully.
Add to this more complete breath a mental
exercise.
Agregale a esta respiración más completa
un foco mental.
El pasaje psíquico frontal.
Una línea imaginaria o tubo en la parte
frontal del torso.
Que va desde el ombligo a través del
esternón hasta el agujerito de la
garganta.
A medida que inhalas, guías respiración
por ese tubo hasta la garganta.
Y en la exhalación, guía la respiración
hacia abajo hasta el ombligo.
Si no viaja por ese camino, no hay
problema.
Continúa enfocando tu mente en la
respiración de una manera gentil.
Con la próxima inhalación, continúa
pasando la garganta hasta el entrefejo.
Mantén tu atención en ese punto,
brumadilla.
Incluso los ojos pueden volverse hacia
adentro y ligeramente hacia arriba,
mirando desde adentro.
Imagina que estás mirando la llama en una
vela.
A veces la imagen aparece, a veces no.
Siempre puedes dibujar la silueta o la
forma de la llama.
Imagina el color o la forma de la llama
que tienes.
De una vela que tú realmente tienes.
Imagínate que esta llama representa el
conocimiento intuitivo disponible dentro
nuestro.
Siempre disponible si miramos hacia
adentro.
Mantra Om tres veces juntos, seguido por
los Shanti Mantras.
Si sabes los mantras, estás bienvenido a
cantar conmigo o simplemente a escuchar.
Respira lento y profundo para cantar el
mantra Om.
Mantra Om
Mantra Om Mantra Om
Sit for just a few more moments in
stillness.
And reflect on what brings you to this
talk this evening.
Any aspirations or questions or intentions
that you may have.
Bring the hands together in pranam mudra,
in front of the heart, move into a round
of palming.
When you have warmth to share with the
eyes, bring the hands in front of the
closed eyes.
And keeping them there for a few moments,
notice if there are any patterns or colors
in chidakash.
The space of the mind.
And take a deep breath in through the eyes
into yourself.
Exhaling, you can lower the hands and
slowly open the eyes.
Hari Om Tat Sat.
I hope wherever you have come from today,
you feel a little bit calmer in this space
that we are in.
The Satyananda Yoga tradition and Swami
Satyananda Saraswati in particular for me
is genius.
You take a practice like Shantipat which
is done at the beginning and the end of
every event.
And it is almost a perfect sequence of
moving through the koshas.
A lesson taught to me through my kung fu
teacher, a lesson taught to me,
was to pay attention to the techniques
that are included the most by a tradition.
And in this tradition, it's chanting the
mantra Om and Shantipat.
So that's a good hint that that technique
can be taken out of a class.
And be applied to any moment in life where
you need to reconnect with your whole
self.
And that's the topic of this evening,
what is the whole self in terms of the
yogic model.
That invites us to look into the koshas or
the five yogic bodies.
How many people here have heard of that
word koshas?
And now I'm gonna flip the question,
how many people is that a new word or term
for?
Good, thanks.
So, thank you.
How many people are working with the
koshas in a daily habit?
Okay, good.
At least one or two or three hands.
I want to inspire more of you to keep the
koshas in daily awareness.
Words in the spiritual traditions like
enlightenment are loaded with promise.
Promise of this moment of glory
and emancipation or freedom.
My very slow evolution has suggested it
may look differently.
And that the real work of evolution is
turning on the light in many places.
In as many places as we can actually find.
For that we need to go on a search.
And luckily many have taken on that
journey before us and drawn out maps.
The kosha model is one such map.
Maps help us avoid crashes in the same way
they helped sailors avoid crashes.
Maps help us find treasure in the same way
they've helped sailors find treasure.
So I'm going to present some ideas around
koshas that hopefully are new to you.
As long as yogic ideas remain theory they
will not be relevant to our personal
lives.
As long as their theory, they're not going
to be the most practical.
We're all of the same cookie cutter mold.
But we all bake differently in the oven.
We really need to customize spirituality
and spiritual practice to ourselves.
How many of you all have heard of chakras?
And how many of you have never heard of
gunas?
If you haven't heard of gunas,
raise your hand.
Okay, great.
So a very yoga aware group here.
So one of the first ideas of kosha is even
though it's five yogic bodies,
it represents a continuum from gross to
subtle.
And before we even get into the five yogic
bodies, there are three bodies that come
before it.
They're often called gross, subtle,
and causal.
And I won't go deep into the details of
the five yogic bodies.
I won't go deep into this.
But our gross body is the tangible body.
The subtle body can be thought of like a
dream body.
Sometimes in a dream you can feel yourself
moving around.
Some traditions call it the astral body.
And even the mental body, I can imagine
being in my home in Nepal moving around.
It's not philosophical.
Humans have this.
That's what makes all of this possible.
We have the ability to move in imagined
spaces.
What's moving around?
Think of that as the subtle body.
Then there's the causal body.
I don't know what that is.
I understand it as an idea that from this
you get this, and from this you get this.
I'm trying to explain that.
And in the longer retreat where we have
many more days, I will get into some ways
of reflecting on the causal body.
Then we can give them the information.
For those of you who have never heard of
the koshas or the five bodies,
we're just going to quickly go over them
now.
And keep in mind that they are just a
subdivision of these three.
So we have the physical body.
And whenever I say one of them,
please take your awareness into it.
Don't let it be a word.
Let it be an experience.
We have the energetic body.
The mental.
The intuitive, or for the moment I'm going
to use the word psychic.
And then again, we reuse the word causal,
also referred to as blissful.
Y vamos a usar de nuevo la palabra causal
o de bienaventuranza.
Voy a decir las palabras en sánscrito
porque indican de qué están hechos estos
cuerpos.
Y para los que han estado estudiando yoga
e integrándola en sus vidas,
realmente les recomiendo que vayan
entrando en algunos términos sánscritos.
This year in particular I have started to
do that with mantras and chants and it's a
whole new dimension.
The cultures that have used Sanskrit for
spirituality put a lot of effort to
accurately describe what they're talking
about.
Han hecho un esfuerzo de hacerlo muy
preciso.
The physical body is called annamayakosha.
El cuerpo físico se llama annamayakosha.
So all of these have mayakosha after them.
Todos tienen mayakosha como terminación.
So anna means food.
Anna significa comida.
So the physical body is made up of food,
it makes sense, the food body.
The energetic body is the pranamayakosha.
Prana can mean energy or life force.
Prana significa energía o fuerza de vida.
This is my preferred understanding.
And one more useful word is vital or
vitality.
Mental is manomayakosha.
El mental es manomayakosha.
Referring to the mind.
Then you have vigyanamaya.
Vigyanamayakosha.
Which both means wisdom or science.
Que significa sabiduría o ciencia.
And if I remember to talk about this in
greater detail, it's so interesting as its
own topic.
And in case I forget to say it many times,
this is what makes us human, I believe.
And then finally we have the
anandamayakosha.
And this is sometimes referred to as
blissful.
But I was reading But I was reading in a
satsang from one of our gurus that it
means undifferentiated.
Y yo leí en uno de los satsangs de los
gurus que significa indiferenciado.
And I want you to consider for a moment
that there is this science-based idea that
things originated from the Big Bang.
Entonces quiero que vean esta idea de que
las cosas se originaron desde el Big Bang.
Some moment where everything was the same
in potential form.
And from that structure and laws of
physics exploded.
And came into being.
Y comenzó a ser.
From that, life started on Earth.
It could move, for example.
Energy systems like photosynthesis came
into being.
Los sistemas energéticos como la
fotosíntesis comenzaron a ocurrir,
ser posibles.
Y la vida evolucionó hasta nuestra forma
corriente como humanos.
So, when we look at the cosas,
in one way it encompasses the evolution of
reality as we know it.
A reality as we understand it right now.
Como la podemos entender ahora mismo.
Para mí esto es muy profundo.
Que toda la historia del universo esté
contenida en este modelo yogico.
Vamos a considerar un modelo yogico de la
mente.
Subconscious.
Como consciente, subconsciente.
And unconscious.
Y inconsciente.
We are invited to go back to where we came
from.
Estamos siendo invitados a volver de donde
venimos.
Not necessarily because that's the goal,
but because that's part of our life
history.
I grew up in America from a small age,
but at some point I felt called to go back
to Nepal.
Yo viví en Norteamérica desde que era un
niño, crecí, pero luego sentí el llamado
de volver a Nepal.
Because I wanted to understand what was
influencing my personality.
Yo quería entender qué estaba
influenciando mi personalidad.
Everything that we're experiencing at a
conscious level is usually an
amplification of the layer just underneath
it.
Todo lo que está sucediendo en un nivel
consciente es usualmente una amplificación
de lo que está sucediendo en la capa que
está por debajo.
For example, the energy in my physical
body usually reflects the quality of
energy that I consumed earlier in the day.
Por ejemplo, cómo me siento físicamente en
mi cuerpo generalmente refleja la calidad
energética, la energía que yo consumo en
el día.
Those choices are usually an amplification
of my mental condition.
Esas decisiones son usualmente una
amplificación de mi condición mental.
If I'm feeling tamásico or slow and heavy,
I'm more likely to go for ice cream and
potato chips.
Just me, I'm not saying about you.
Si estoy sintiéndome tamásico o lento,
pesado, seguramente esté más inclinado a
ir a buscar helado o papas, papas fritas.
Eso es lo que me sucede a mí.
If I'm feeling very energetic,
I'm more likely to go for watermelon or a
sports drink.
Cuando estoy más energético, estoy más
inclinado a ir por watermelon o alguna
bebida deportiva.
If I'm feeling balanced and I don't want
to disrupt that, I'll go for a food that I
know doesn't change my mental state.
Y si estoy en equilibrio y quiero mantener
ese estado de equilibrio, voy a ir a
buscar una comida que no afecte este nivel
mental que yo tengo.
Those internal preferences are largely
influenced by things like culture,
education, and media.
I think I'll stop there because I don't
know what else to say about that.
But I want you to see that, consider that
things from lower levels build until we
make a choice.
Entonces considerar que cosas desde
niveles más bajos van creciendo hasta que
hacemos elecciones.
Se van construyendo.
So if we find ourselves in any life
situation and wonder, how did I get here?
Entonces podemos vernos en alguna
situación de vida y preguntarnos,
¿cómo llegué hasta acá?
Then the koshas as a map say, I think we
can discover that together.
Entonces los koshas como mapa pueden
decirnos, creo que podemos descubrir esto
juntos.
And this is where the various yoga
techniques become very useful lenses.
Y acá es cuando toda esta variedad de
técnicas de yoga se convierten en lentes
muy útiles.
For systematically analyzing and
remediating any imbalance.
Para sistemáticamente analizar y remediar
cualquier desequilibrio.
In any of these five, I'm going to say
four levels for now.
En cualquiera de estos niveles,
va a decir ahora en esos cuatro niveles,
por ahora.
Because it's assumed that the fifth
represents an already balanced state.
Porque se asume que el quinto ya
representa un estado de equilibrio.
So at a high level, this is one of the
ideas on how to use the koshas in a real
way.
Entonces esta es una de las ideas de cómo
utilizar los koshas de una manera real.
Do a quick time check.
¿Cómo vamos?
We've been already sitting for a few
moments.
And because the talk is supposed to be
experience as well, we're going to do some
movements.
Ya que estuvieron sentados por un momento
y también esta charla es con práctica,
vamos a hacer algunos movimientos.
I'm always trying to think what techniques
can we do in a short talk that are
beneficial to the physical body.
Siempre estoy pensando qué técnicas
podemos hacer en una charla corta que sean
beneficiosas para el cuerpo físico.
And that usually resolves to what
movements will move the spine in the most
directions.
Y esto generalmente se resume en qué
movimientos van a mover la columna en la
mayor cantidad de direcciones.
The spinal cord is deeply connected to our
energetic system and to our brain.
La columna vertebral está muy conectado a
nuestro sistema energético y a nuestro
cerebro.
So if you know anyone in your network who
wants to improve their overall condition
Entonces si sabes de alguien que quiera
mejorar su condición general But claims
they don't have much time Pero te dice que
tienen poco tiempo As a yoga practitioner,
please give them practices that touch
multiple cosas.
Entonces como practicante de yoga,
compartile prácticas que toquen múltiples
cosas.
This is one reason I start every retreat
with shatkarma.
Esa es la razón por la que comienzo
cualquier retiro con shatkarma.
You cannot poop water out of your butt.
No puedes sacar agua de tu cuerpo.
Ah, de tu ano.
Without wondering what's going on inside
your physical body.
Sin tener una idea de lo que está pasando
en tu cuerpo físico.
It will not only help you feel the
internal plumbing No solo te va a ayudar a
sentir tu bombeo interno But it usually
brings immediate change in energy,
either low or high.
Eso también va a traer un cambio inmediato
a nivel energético Tanto hacia arriba como
hacia abajo.
When you've washed all the food out of
your system, many people are able to feel
a shift in the mind.
Cuando sacaste toda la comida fuera de tu
sistema, muchas personas también pueden
sentir, darse cuenta del cambio a nivel
mental.
Internationally, indigenous cultures have
used plants as medicines and exploration
tools.
Internacionalmente, los indígenas han
usado plantas como medicina y sustancias
de exploración.
Many of those ceremonies ask the
individual to fast.
Y muchas de estas ceremonias le piden al
individuo ayunar.
Many people think it's to reduce the
amount of vomiting if the medicine invokes
that.
Mucha gente cree que es para reducir la
cantidad de vómitos si la medicina lo
provoca.
But the subtler aspect is you can't feel
the influence of your psyche if food is
changing the way the mind behaves.
Pero la parte más sutil de esta es que no
puedes darte cuenta de los cambios a nivel
mental si la comida te está influenciando.
So how do you know if what insights you
have are from the energy of the food or
from your unconscious?
¿Cómo sabes si los insights que estás
teniendo son un efecto que viene de la
comida o si es algo que viene de tu
inconsciente?
Shivaratri is this coming Saturday.
¿El shivaratri va a ser el próximo sábado?
Traditionally, even now, people will fast
for 12 to 24 hours.
Some people fast from eating.
I know people who fast from drinking a
drop of water for 24 hours.
Y hay personas que también ayunan en tomar
agua por esas 24 horas.
Algunos ayunan de dormir por esas 24
horas.
Ese tipo de prácticas pueden darse cuenta
que van a estresar estos cuerpos.
Cuando los sistemas se estresan,
tienden a empujar lo que estaba acumulado.
That's one of the biological benefits of
food fasting.
It detoxes the digestive system.
Ese es uno de los beneficios del ayuno,
que desintoxica el sistema.
What is energetic or pranic fasting?
What is mental fasting for you?
What is psychic or intuitive fasting?
These are the questions I want you to walk
away with.
Any technique can be applied to any kosha,
especially the first four.
We tend to work with the physical body
because it's the most accessible.
Tendemos a trabajar más con el cuerpo
físico porque es el más accesible.
Pero a medida que tienes más experiencia y
maestría, queremos entrar en niveles más
sutiles.
Una vez que hayas alcanzado la maestría en
una asana física, See if you can do it in
your dream as well.
If you've never done a yoga class in your
dream, why not?
You have to train yourself to wake up
while you're sleeping.
And have the focus of mind to do your
sadhana when you could be flying or diving
under the ocean.
That takes a lot of willpower that when
you can do anything you want, you choose
to do asanas.
Eso te puede dar mucho poder mental.
Cuando puedes hacer una cosa, haces
asanas.
Pero los efectos son únicos.
Puedes hacer cosas con tu cuerpo astral
que no puedes hacer con tu cuerpo físico.
Ese poder de voluntad es una de las formas
de aumentar el cuerpo de dicha o acceder.
Yo le he preguntado casi a toda persona
que encuentro la siguiente pregunta.
Si tratas de levantar la mano de tu
pierna, ¿Por qué poder eres capaz de hacer
eso?
¿Cuál es el poder que te permite levantar
la mano de tu pierna?
Puedes intentarlo ahora.
¿Cómo pudiste hacer eso?
¿Y qué fue lo que le mandó esa instrucción
a la mente de hacer eso?
A desire, an intention.
You heard the words and you thought,
ok, I will.
Escuchaste las palabras y dijiste,
ok, lo voy a hacer.
That intention is an act of one's will.
To my knowledge, there is no scientific,
biological way to explain intent or will.
Para mi conocimiento, no hay una ciencia o
algo que explique la intención o la
voluntad.
En yoga y la tradición tántrica,
la primer Shakti, energía, es Isha.
First there was the intention that
something comes into being.
Willpower comes from a very, very,
very ancient source.
¿La voluntad, willpower?
Fuerza de voluntad.
Viene de una fuente muy, muy antigua.
La fuerza de voluntad puede superar
limitaciones físicas.
limitaciones energéticas.
En Australia, un niño de 12 años se tiró
al océano para salvar a su familia que
estaba en el mar.
Cuando le preguntaron cómo lo hiciste,
él dijo que fue una fuerza de voluntad,
él simplemente quería salvarlos.
No tenían tantas chances de sobrevivir.
La fuerza de voluntad también permite
superar limitaciones mentales.
La fuerza de voluntad también te va a
conectar con soluciones que vienen de la
educación, de la cultura, de otros
lugares.
Una de las mejores herramientas que nos da
la tradición de Satyananda es la del
sankalpa.
La primera práctica que hacemos cuando nos
levantamos, los sankalpas para los mantras
de la mañana.
Idealmente, también el último pensamiento
en tu mente cuando te vas a dormir,
el sankalpa.
Idealmente, que se repite cada vez que nos
involucramos, antes de involucrarnos en
cualquier acción.
Practicamos esto con asanas y pranayama.
Para visualizar lo que vamos a hacer,
incluso antes de hacerlo.
Pero si solo limitamos esa práctica al
mat, estamos perdiendo el punto de por qué
lo estamos enseñando.
Yo escuché que cuando Swamiji vio uno de
los templos que se construyó en Australia,
él finalmente lo vio y dijo, ah,
justo como lo imaginé.
Y el Chaya Samadhi de la Escuela de Bihar
es bien documentado como él lo concibió y
manifestó.
Y lo mismo respecto a los trabajos de
Swami Satyananda.
Tenían muy desarrollada la visualización y
la fuerza de voluntad.
Si la semilla es suficientemente
desarrollada con una visión, it will
manifest according to that plan.
The whole point of that was for the
practice.
Welcome to my mind.
Bienvenidos a mi mente.
Todo esto era para introducir la práctica.
I'm still working on a number of koshas.
So I want to see, can a number of you,
can anyone not come into squatting?
I will provide an alternative.
We just do two movements that are very
good for everyday development of the
spine.
That's perfect, you can do it from sitting
and you can try it from a chair if you'd
like.
The first practice is namaskar asana with
the hands in pranamudra.
The head starts in a relaxed downward
position.
And as you straighten the spine,
bring the hands to the chest and push the
knees open.
And if your spine comfortably allows,
push the sternum up and look up.
And then reversing back to the starting
point, knees closed, arms stretched.
Inhale as you straighten and look up.
Exhale as you fold forward and stretch.
Up to three more times on your own.
Awareness in the spine and spinal
sensations.
That's it for the first practice.
Wherever you are, make this your last
round.
And for the second practice, place your
fingers underneath the soles of the feet
from the inside of your legs.
We're going to look up, breathe in.
And then exhaling, straighten the legs any
amount and head towards the knees.
And then we're going to look up,
breathe in.
And then exhaling, straighten the legs any
amount Inhaling, coming back to the
squatting while you straighten and look
up.
Exhaling, straightening and lowering the
head.
And do that up to three more times.
When you're finished, you can sit in a
comfortable cross-legged position.
And close the eyes for a few moments,
the hands in a mudra.
Reflect on those two practices.
Which parts of your physical body you
actually felt.
Whether it was in the bones or muscles.
Tendons or ligaments.
Organs, including the skin.
If you were to design a practice that
touched every body system,
which practices would you include and
imagine that for a few moments?
How does that compare to the current
practices you have?
And is there anything you would be willing
to change in your sadhana to bring you
closer to a deeper connection to your
body's systems?
Take a few deep breaths in and out.
Bring the hands into pranamudra and then
palming.
Notice how much the hands are moving.
Notice how much warmth can be felt.
Try and intensify it.
When you bring those palms to the eyes,
feel the heat or warmth on the skin.
When you breathe that warmth in through
the eyes, imagine the color of light
moving into the brain.
And exhale that warmth and prana down the
whole nervous system.
And then gently lower the hands.
Arya Om Tat Sat.
That type of approach is one way you can
deepen any practice.
My experiences were given dozens of
techniques not to master all of them.
But to discover the two or three that
works as keys for our individual koshas.
Meru Dandasana, where you balance on your
tailbone in a V position.
I know from experience that can calm my
mind even if I'm feeling rage.
It has been tested multiple times.
I'm not going to do another asana because
I found one that goes into different
koshas immediately.
I know that this practice can calm my mind
even if I'm feeling rage.
That Kumbhak after Kapalabhati with
Padmasana will bring me much closer to
Vidyanamaya Kosha.
I know because I've tried five different
meditation asanas.
And many pranayamas for weeks with a
journal.
So please find those practices that bring
you into contact with each of these
koshas.
So please find those practices that bring
you into contact with each of these
koshas.
If you don't have that map or key for
yourself, then you have to question for
how long you're just going to follow
someone else's instruction.
Most of us do not want to live our lives
just doing what someone else tells us to.
And yet on the spiritual path,
that's where many of us stay.
I want to go into an idea of how each of
these bodies takes input the same way.
How we consume.
And I want you to question what I'm saying
to see if that seems true to you.
And if not, to push back on me in a
moment.
Is everyone doing okay so far with the
level of the talk?
I'm not changing it now, so you have to
say yes, but still I'm curious.
Intake?
Intake.
Ingestion or digestion.
Filtering and sorting.
Repartir or seleccionar.
Integration.
And elimination.
Everyone okay with the words?
This is really interesting from the
perspective of the four ashramas.
The four life stages.
Some of you all have heard of the four
life stages?
What's the first one?
The first ashrama.
Childhood.
Do you all know the Sanskrit name?
Brahmacharya.
This is the stage of the student or the
learner.
What's the second stage?
Grihastha.
That's the householder.
I'm going to call that like living.
You're now living your life.
Here you're learning.
First you're learning about life and now
you're living your life.
What is the third stage?
These are relevant because we're all going
through them whether we want to or not.
I did a retreat once in Brazil and out of
the three days someone said the most
useful thing for me was just to hear the
life stages.
I've also found the same.
It's another map.
The third stage is vanaprastha.
It means forest dweller.
What's the difference between people who
live in the city and people who live in
the forest?
Many of them.
People in the forest usually have less
stuff.
Between these two stages there's a lot of
filtering and sorting.
What do I need?
What do I want?
And the fourth is sannyasa.
Or renunciation.
Or detachment.
So look for a moment between learning,
intaking, consuming
experiencing letting go and completely
detaching.
Taking in chewing and integrating
at some point deciding what's useful,
what's not
and then pushing out everything that
doesn't help growth.
Even though these are talked about in
terms of one whole life
we actually go through these stages every
single day.
We all go through the morning where
there's something that we want to do we
review how yesterday went or the week
we act out those goals we experience them
we reflect on what got done, didn't get
done what worked or didn't work
and hopefully by night time we let it go
knowing that we get another day
or another life to start the process
again.
This same process happens in the physical
body
you eat you digest you sort you build your
body and then you poop.
This can be done for the energetic body
What are you consuming let me skip this
for a moment look at the mental body
In yogic perspective we don't just eat
through this orifice we eat through all
the holes in our body
What is the quality of the air in your
apartment or home
What are you listening to What are you
listening to in the car or from the people
that you interact with?
What are you taking in through your eyes,
your tongue, your sexual organs?
Everything that goes in is going to be
digested?
Hopefully filtered and sorted well.
Integrated.
And hopefully the unuseful eliminated.
If these two, if this one is not working
well, what you integrate may not be of
great quality.
And if this is not working well,
life becomes unsustainable.
How many people, you don't have to raise
your hand, how many of you know someone
who rents extra storage because there is
not enough space to contain what you
already have?
I have five hard drives.
I have five hard drives of data I will
never revisit.
Hard drive?
Hard drive, external drive.
And when one of those finally dies,
I grieve deeply.
I really do because it represents years of
memories.
And effort.
It doesn't matter that I never open any of
those files.
I'm deeply attached to them and so I carry
the baggage that one day these will
disappear.
The ashram life is really good at bringing
this back into a state of health.
You're constantly being told to move
rooms.
You get tired of carrying stuff.
And over a number of years you learn to
live with what is essential to you.
That's practical sannyasa.
It's not a high spiritual idea.
What do I need to lead a simple,
happy life?
That's sannyasa.
But those needs are going to be different
for each body.
And so that raises the question,
what is required for each body?
What nourishes each kosha?
And the same question, what happens when
they're undernourished?
I want to present a model for you that has
worked really well for me.
Last year I gave talks in Uruguay.
Related to an experience I had with acute
anxiety and depression.
And it really surprised me because I was
physically fit.
I thought I had a really high level of
energy.
But all of a sudden, my mental and psychic
condition collapsed.
And it happened so suddenly, it forced the
question, how did this happen outside of
my awareness?
So I want you to imagine a four-legged,
square table.
And that each of these legs are the first
four koshas.
And that each leg of the table is one of
these four koshas.
Physical, energetic, mental, intuitive.
If you take away just any one of these
legs, Si tu sacas una de estas cuatro
patas, La mesa se cae o se mantiene?
Es una mesa cuadrada.
It's standing because it has a triangular
base.
There is a big if there.
I'm not an artist, sorry.
If you put anything on the corner with the
missing leg, that table falls.
So what can happen and has happened in
many of our lives,
We have three legs and the table is stable
because nothing has been put on that
fourth corner.
And as soon as something unexpected
happens, job loss, death in the family,
heartbreak,
If that was your psychic or mental leg,
that can be enough to have a momentary
breakdown.
Let me give you another type of table.
It's one with four legs.
And they're all of different lengths.
How many of you have a table like this in
your house?
Really?
Almost nobody because those tables don't
hold things well.
So you buy a nice crystal bowl.
You put it on that table and it falls off
a few seconds later.
How many of you have experienced this in
life?
You work hard to achieve something.
And within weeks or years, it just seems
to come out of your life even though you
want it to stay.
If that has happened to you, please
measure the legs of your tables.
The yogic tools are partly measurement
tools.
They're diagnostic tools.
How flexible are you?
How much strength do you have in different
muscles?
What is your balance like?
How smoothly can your joints move?
How long can you hold your breath?
Can you regulate your body temperature?
What are your natural sleep and digestive
cycles?
How good are you at filtering stimuli?
How strong is your memory?
How precise is your visualization?
How often do you have clear solutions in
your mind?
How deeply can you feel any emotion?
Can you laugh or cry at will?
These are all some ways of assessing the
health of our koshas.
There are dozens of yogic tools for
measuring each of these kosha legs.
Satyananda Yoga is particularly good at
emphasizing developing all of them.
Because at some point, as we begin to move
into our whole being, we want these to be
balanced as possible.
That's the metaphor of the table.
I have one more for y'all.
But just before we do, to give the mind a
break, we're going to do a simple
meditation.
Give your legs a stretch if you've been
sitting cross-legged for a bit.
And then come back into any comfortable
sitting asana.
Ideally something stable and that creates
balance through the whole body.
Hands in a mudra of your choice,
resting somewhere on the legs or lap.
Feeling to the position of the neck and
head.
Take a deep breath in, feeling the whole
body expand.
And when you exhale, imagine that all the
muscles soften around the bones.
Do this two more times on your own.
Use the mind and the visualization
along with the actual breath to create a
state of softness and relaxation in the
physical body.
After the third breath in that manner,
move into subtle, full yogic breathing.
Subtle, full yogic breathing.
In this breath, it is soft, almost silent.
But you are still filling the lungs with
air without strain.
Feeling to the whole left side of the
body.
Imagine only the left half.
Feeling the sensations amplified in the
left half of the body.
And in the mind's eye, feeling the whole
right half is blacked out and feeling and
seeing the left half.
Now switch to the right half only.
In the mental visualization of yourself,
there is no left half, only right side.
In your physical awareness, you are
concentrating on the right half only.
And amplifying or experiencing sensations
on the right side.
Now move back awareness in the left half.
As you feel the body and the sensations in
the left side,
imagine that the left nasal passage is the
only one that breathes in.
When you breathe out, shift the focus to
the right side.
Physical awareness, sensory awareness,
breathing out the right.
Then inhale through the right.
And switch completely physical to
visualization with the left.
Continue this for a number of rounds.
Mental Navishodhana.
But using physical awareness
of that side of the body that's breathing.
Aware of the breath in that half only.
And visualizing that half only.
If any one kosha begins to dim,
become less present, it's no problem just
to be aware of that.
Sometimes we lose physical awareness.
Sometimes we lose pranic awareness.
Sometimes there is an absence of mental
focus.
And sometimes there is an absence of the
deep feeling or visualization.
The next time you exhale from the left
side, begin to breathe in through both
nasal passages.
Imagine and feel your whole body.
The expansion and contraction of your
whole body with each breath in and out.
Following each and every breath from the
moment it enters to the moment it leaves
the body.
And the feeling of your life being
extended by another five minutes with each
breath.
Bring the hands into pranamudra and move
into a round of palms.
Notice if the temperature has stayed the
same or changed.
When you have heat to share, bring them
close to the closed eyes.
Notice any patterns or colors or shapes
that may or may not be present.
Inhale that warmth back into you through
the eyes.
And exhaling, you can lower the hands and
open the eyes slowly.
Almost all of us, maybe all of us,
have done nadi shodhana.
I have found that so much emphasis remains
on the breathing pattern that we never
experiment beyond that.
The pranas are so subtle.
In 20 years, I have distinctly felt prana,
without a doubt, maybe twice.
You have some minutes to end.
I mean very distinctly, like some.
Not just general energy.
If we run, we feel hot.
That's a change in prana.
But to feel apana moving down.
Or samana moving back and forth.
Or udana moving through the outward lens.
I find those are harder to contact because
I'm not demanding that of myself.
Before I introduce the second model,
I want to say two more things about the
table metaphor.
We talked about one way of toppling the
table is if a leg is missing.
More often, it's that our legs are of
different lengths, and so the table is
imbalanced.
But there's another case where the table
is...
the legs are the same length, but not all
the legs are the same length.
Or of the same strength.
This goes back to that intake,
digestion, integration.
So, for example, if the quality of prana
we intake is low, or tamasic,
based on what we're eating, the air we're
breathing,
and whatever we're consuming with our
other senses, including the mind,
what can happen is, for a long time,
we start to add to our intake,
add things to the table with confidence,
not realizing that this leg is stable,
but has a maximum weight it can carry.
And even though the whole table is doing a
good job,
we put one more thing on the compromised
leg,
and it shatters.
And because there's weights everywhere,
the table falls.
This is almost the worst situation to be
in, because it gives a sense of false
confidence.
And yet, I have found myself multiple
times in that situation.
And nearly every time I look back at what
compromised that leg,
what compromised that yogic body,
it was because I was not selective or
careful about how I was nourishing it.
We won't have time tonight, but I want to
give you all a simple practice,
or exercise rather, and luckily we live in
times where access to information is
fairly easy with books and the internet.
And the exercise is to take each of the
yogic bodies, especially the first four,
and to write down everything that you
believe is a subsystem or component of
that body.
So let's take an example like the physical
body, the Anamaya Kosha.
We've got muscles or muscular system.
We've had bones, organs, what else?
Joints, ligaments, what's that?
Arteries.
Veins, arteries.
You can say circulatory system.
And let's even include hormones,
because they're powerful.
And this is what happens when you go to
the doctor.
This is modern biology.
They're really good at the Anamaya Kosha.
X-rays,
PET scans, MRIs,
sonograms, is that what they're called?
You know, we can see so many layers now of
the Anamaya Kosha.
And they can tell you, oh, you had a
stroke ten years ago, in this part of the
brain.
It's amazing.
So, what are some of the subsystems of the
energetic body, the pranic body?
What are some of the subsystems of the
What do you think?
Breathing,
Breathing, Movement, Movement,
Maybe movement, yes.
These aren't always in one category,
obviously.
Maybe metabolism.
And the point I want to make is,
we have some classical ones.
For example, the five sub-pranas.
And so, what you will notice is,
if you look at the mind, in the yogic
model, even the mind is broken down into
classical four categories.
And if we go to the mental plane,
we see that even the mind is categorized
into four subsystems, like manas,
chitta, buddhi, and ahamkara.
And it has to do the same with the psychic
body, which includes the chakras.
So when someone asks you, how are you
doing, we have very general responses.
Ok, fine.
But when you ask yourself, which I hope
you are doing, at least twice a day,
because the beginning of the day can feel
very different than the end of the day,
we want that question to automatically go
into a process of how am I feeling,
how am I feeling, how am I feeling,
how am I feeling.
How am I feeling?
That is kosha scanning.
In the beginning that might feel like work
because we haven't exercised it.
But when that becomes familiar,
it's like doing a talk with zoom on,
with a translator and people in front of
you.
Each of us are aware of so many things
right now, including what you are going to
have for dinner, whether your son or
daughter did their homework, what your
interaction with your partner is going to
be, what traffic is projected to be.
We are all supercomputers calculating a
lot.
But a lot of that mental awareness may not
be directly benefiting our connection to
ourself.
And if you find that's the case for you
based on your table toppling,
then you have at least one simple exercise
to just check what your awareness of each
body actually is.
Tienes este ejercicio para chequear cuál
es tu conciencia, tu nivel de conciencia
en cada uno de estos niveles.
And if you find that there is a lack of
awareness in any of these bodies,
the question is how do I bring awareness
into that body.
Y si hay falta de conciencia en alguno de
estos cuerpos, la pregunta es cómo puedo
empezar a traer conciencia a este cuerpo.
Eso esencialmente es lo que es el yoga.
We don't need so many techniques,
so I don't want this to feel overwhelming,
it doesn't have to be.
Hay tantas técnicas, yo no quiero que esto
se vuelva algo abrumador.
Pero tiene que ser intencional,
que hacerlo intencionalmente.
And that intention and the quality and
degree of it will come through the
remainder of the body.
Y esa intención va a ir por el resto de
los cuerpos, se va a traducir en el resto
de los cuerpos.
There is a question here in the chat.
Yeah, let's take it because we are running
out of time.
She is asking what are the five supranas
and the four parts of the body,
of the mental body.
The five pranas which are available in all
the BSY books like Prana and Pranayama and
online are Apana, moving down.
Prana, moving up.
Samana, side to side.
Udana, in the limbs.
And Vyana, around the whole body,
the buffer prana.
Los cinco pranas que los puedes encontrar
en todos los libros de Bihar School of
Yoga son Apana, que se mueve hacia abajo,
el ombligo hacia abajo.
Prana, hacia arriba.
Samana, hacia los costados.
Udana, las extremidades.
Y la última es Vyana, que es el que está
alrededor de todo el cuerpo.
Eso lo puedes encontrar Vyana en los
libros, muy bien explicado.
Y las cuatro partes del cuerpo mental,
las nombramos, pero es más complejo.
Manas, chitta, buddhi y ajankara.
Eso también te podemos dar alguna
referencia en el libro para que después lo
investigues.
¿Han escuchado estos términos de cómo se
clasifica el cuerpo mental, mano,
mano y apoya?
Son realmente valientes de visitar,
porque para muchos de nosotros en esta
sala, que son más de 30, vale la pena
visitar estos, porque todos los que
estamos en este salón, que tenemos más de
30,
porque algunas categorías de nuestro
cuerpo mental van a empezar a mostrar
falta de mantenimiento.
Memorias, percepción, discernimiento y la
toma de decisiones.
Incluso el sentido del ser y del ego
saludable.
Voy a leer algunas prácticas que tenemos
disponibles desde nuestra tradición.
Esto puede parecer obvio y está bueno,
si parece obvio.
Y si no,
es alimento para pensar.
Muchas de estas técnicas benefician a
múltiples cuerpos yógicos.
Las asanas obviamente para el cuerpo
físico, pero también para el cuerpo
energético y mental.
Pranayama, obviamente que beneficia al
cuerpo energético, pero también el mental
y el intuitivo.
Dharana, contemplation, very good for
mental and intuitive.
¿Cuál es la práctica de dharana simple que
hemos hecho hoy?
La conciencia por el pasaje frontal.
Es una herramienta tan buena para
introducir la meditación.
Porque estás concentrándote en un camino,
dejando que la mente se mueva por ahí.
Yoga Nidra beneficia a todo, físico a
causal.
And can give people experiences of each
body in isolation and in unison.
Mantra, especially with the sankopas,
for causal body and psychic body.
Mantra para el cuerpo causal e intuitivo.
La meditación del swan puede servir para
hacer un balance de las fortalezas y
debilidades de cada uno de esos cuerpos.
Ideas of what each of these bodies are
made of.
And one of the best is Karma Yoga and
Seva, because that reflects how well
integrated we are in actual daily life.
You might lift weights perfectly in a gym,
but if you can't lift boxes between rooms,
what's the point?
And that goes for the other bodies as
well.
Sometimes the skills we have in certain
situations aren't transferable.
Karma Yoga invites us to develop skills
that are applicable to all aspects of
life.
It helps us sort, filter and eliminate
what's worth developing and what may not
need to be developed in our current life
stage.
It helps us sort, filter and eliminate
what's applicable to life and what's
better to let go.
That's the time we have, because for now,
by now, for now.
For now.
I really hope that you heard something
that makes you think or feel differently
about the koshas.
About your personal sadhana.
And about your relationship to the entire
Yoga Vidya.
There are no rules or limits on how you
can make this knowledge your own.
And so I want to thank you for letting me
share some of my own connections I've
made.
There is a retreat at Yoga 104 from the
13th to the 17th, I think.
And each day we're focusing on a
particular kosha.
And we've invited speakers from the
community as well to talk about their
experience with that kosha.
Y hemos invitado personas que van a estar
hablando sobre su experiencia con este
kosha, expertos de la comunidad.
I really wanted to hear from someone who
cuts into the physical body, an autopsist.
I think Janardhan found a doctor who has
that experience.
We have someone who works with cancer
patients and how that has revealed to them
something about the human spirit.
We have a speaker who's worked with autism
in children and she will come on the
Manomaya day.
And very exciting, we have 24 hours of
kirtan from Saturday, 24.
We need your help.
Tenemos 24 horas continua de kirtan desde
el sábado a las 5 de la tarde,
a las 7 de la tarde hasta el domingo,
24.
Va a ser una mezcla entre bailar,
mantra, javan, yoga nidra...
para que en las 24 horas le demos también
descanso a cada uno de los cuerpos.
Entonces si alguno de ustedes quiere tener
esta experiencia o conoce a alguien,
están invitados de corazón.
And with that we will do a short shantipa.
Bring the body into any comfortable
position.
One where the spine is upright in
alignment with the neck and head.
Hands in a mudra of your choice,
eyes and mouth gently closed.
Bring the awareness to the eyebrow center
and visualize a steady golden flame.
Or a bright point of light.
With our awareness on that inner light,
we will chant the mantra OM three times
together.
Followed by OM shanti, shanti,
shanti, hari OM.
Slow full breath in to chant the mantra
OM.
A deep and slow breath in to chant the
mantra OM.
Hari OM.
Thank you all very much.
I did not leave time for questions and
answers but if you connect with Bhakti
Mai, I will definitely answer every
question by text of what I know.