Hari Om Tat Sat.
Namaste to everyone.
My name is Satchitananda.
I recognize some of you, and there are
some new faces here today as well.
My sincere gratitude for making time to
come to this presentation.
For any of us who are exploring anything
deeply, you know how valuable it is to be
able to reflect that information.
To reflect that information.
As part of the process of digestion and
integration.
I am a yoga practitioner for over two
decades now, and have also gone deep into
other modalities like Shaolin Kung Fu.
Lots of time in nature, and lots of time
in the office with the laptop as well.
I only mention that to say that this talk
will hopefully be an integration of my
background.
And as such, will hopefully present
something in a different perspective than
you may have encountered before.
Most of all, I hope that you feel inspired
to create models of understanding that
feel real and practical to your life.
It's taken me about twenty-five years of
exposure to this information.
And a couple of big waves in life.
To make the Vidya accessible in a way that
really makes a difference to positivity in
my life.
My main training in yoga is from
Satyananda Yoga.
But I'm not a representative of the ashram
in any way, and that also gives me the
freedom to speak my thoughts freely.
If there's something you disagree with,
or you feel isn't a version you've heard,
please know that's my version,
and you can go to the ashram to get the
original version.
If there's something you disagree with,
or you feel isn't a version you've heard,
please know that's my version,
and you can go to the ashram to get the
original version.
We'll be doing a few practices.
As with all practices, I don't know your
background, so you have the option to just
watch, rather than participate.
You got distracted?
All practices are optional.
Be reasonable in anything you do.
Everything will be very basic this
evening.
I also like to make comments on psychology
and physiology.
I'm not a registered psychologist or a
doctor.
No es doctor, recibido, ni psicólogo.
Así que los invito a que cualquier duda lo
verifiquen.
Entonces vamos a empezar con el Shantipat.
Shantipat is a way for all of us to just
sink in, independent of where we came from
this evening.
So please bring yourself into a
comfortable sitting position.
Ideally where the legs provide a stable,
balanced base.
For the spine, neck and head.
Spine comfortably upright.
Neck balanced on the shoulders.
Head balanced on the neck.
Arms relaxed and the hands optionally in a
mudra.
A simple one is to touch the tips of the
index fingers to the thumb.
If comfortable, eyes gently closed.
Los ojos cómodamente y suavemente
cerrados.
As well as the mouth.
Sit with yourself and give time to settle
within your body.
Siéntese con ustedes mismos y denle tiempo
al cuerpo para que se asienten.
En este proceso está bueno sentir las
partes principales del cuerpo.
Especialmente aquellas partes que están en
contacto con el suelo.
Las partes que se tocan unas con otras.
Y las partes que están en contacto con el
aire.
As you become aware of any body part,
add that to the mental image of how you're
sitting right now.
Try and create a complete visualization of
how you're sitting by actually feeling
that part.
Completa visualización de cómo están
sentados.
Notice that within the stillness of the
body, the breath is moving on its own.
Sea consciente de que a medida que el
cuerpo se va quietando, la respiración
igual se va moviendo en forma
independiente.
Without feeling the need to change it,
notice where it can be felt, how deep.
Sin necesidad de modificarla, la
respiración, sientan en qué parte del
cuerpo se siente y cuán profunda es.
In this process of internalization,
it's very common for impressions of the
day or the week to present themselves.
En este proceso de internalización,
es muy probable que vengan imágenes de
hechos que sucedieron en el día o durante
la semana.
There's no conflict with the mind at this
point.
But it can be really helpful to just step
back and be the witness of any mental
activity.
And whenever possible, come back to
following the breath in and out of
yourself.
Vuelvan a concentrarse en la respiración y
a seguir a ver cómo estaban respirando.
Empiecen a profundizar en la respiración,
a hacerla más profunda en las dos
direcciones.
Muy de a poco, pero progresivamente.
De manera tal que cada nueva respiración
sea un poquito más profunda que la
anterior en las dos direcciones.
Y a esta respiración le vamos a agregar un
foco mental.
Un circuito imaginario desde el ombligo al
esternón y a la garganta.
Pueden imaginarlo como una vía del tren o
como un tubo.
De manera tal que a medida que van
respirando, van sintiendo cómo el aire
sube a través del ombligo hasta la
garganta.
Y cuando exhalan, van sintiendo cómo la
respiración baja desde la garganta,
esternón y ombligo.
Pueden visualizar este movimiento como una
luz o como una sensación.
Cualquier técnica que le ayude a la mente
a mantenerse conectada con la respiración.
Moviéndose hacia arriba y hacia abajo en
este pasaje psíquico frontal.
Y con la próxima inhalación sigan
haciéndose recorrido que pase a través de
la garganta y siga hasta el entresejo.
Y ahora empiecen a respirar hacia adentro
y hacia afuera por el entresejo.
Es como si la inhalación perforara el
entresejo y se mueve hasta el centro del
cerebro.
Sintiendo esa región de la cabeza que se
llena de prana, de vitalidad.
Y al exhalar, sientan que la respiración
baja de la garganta.
La respiración y la atención se mueven
desde el centro del cerebro a través del
entresejo hacia el exterior.
Y ahora dejen que la mente se estabilice
al punto del entresejo, en el punto del
entresejo, se enfoque en el punto del
entresejo.
La forma de una llama dorada.
Visualicen la forma, el color.
Pueden hasta sentir el calor.
Y si no aparece ninguna imagen,
mantengan la idea de que hay una luz en
ese punto.
Y concentrados en esta luz interior,
cantamos tres veces el mantra OM.
Y los chanti mantras de apertura,
todos juntos también.
Y si no estás familiarizado con los
mantras, escuchá el sonido y sentí cómo
vibran en ti.
Respiramos lento y profundo.
Frote las palmas una con la otra,
esto se llama palming.
La idea es crear calor entre las palmas.
Y cuando tengan ese calor, posan sobre los
ojos y comparten el calor con los ojos.
Y sean conscientes de lo que ven en ese
espacio oscuro.
Y después con una inhalación, expandan ese
calor en ustedes mismos.
Y mientras exhalan, bajan las manos.
Esta práctica de Shantipat para mí es un
ejemplo de la genialidad de Swami
Satyananda.
Para los que no lo conocen, es el
individuo en la parte derecha de la archa.
¿Qué es lo que se llama ahí de la derecha?
Una práctica simple del Shantipat hace que
la conciencia rote a través de todos los
koshas.
Para que cada parte del cuerpo que
queremos, de nosotros mismos, que queremos
conocer un poco más en profundidad,
tiene que ser repetida miles de veces.
Porque dice que toma mucho tiempo
profundizar y hacer una conexión genuina
con esa parte.
Y hace que el tiempo de repetirlo,
es el tiempo que se tarda, que se necesita
para crear esa conexión.
Cada uno de nosotros somos expertos en
nuestra área de conocimiento.
Y cuando ponemos el foco, le damos control
a ese entorno, a ese espacio, esa parte es
como que realmente empieza a brillar.
Pero afuera de ese entorno que no tenemos
control,
no le cuesta mucho la vida voltear.
¿Y usted se siente identificado con esto?
Dice que con un poco de práctica,
él se puede meter en sus sueños y trabajar
en su inconsciente.
Cuando tiene que cantar mantras frente a
500 personas en el ashram, dice que se
duerme y cabecea el micrófono.
Eso es la parte opuesta de que cada uno
nos vivimos.
Podemos ser unos psicólogos expertos,
aconsejar a otros para arreglar
relaciones, y podemos no saber cómo hablar
con nuestra pareja o con nuestros hijos.
Y cada uno puede encontrar sus propios
ejemplos en la vida.
Repetir algo muchas veces es como que
termina estableciendo una conexión,
entonces empieza a haber menos contraste
entre un ambiente controlado y un ambiente
espontáneo.
Esa es la motivación para un yogi y para
una yogi.
Esta es la motivación para cualquiera que
quiera explorar en la conciencia.
quiera explorar en la Tierra.
Los océanos.
El espacio.
Puede ser el espacio externo o el espacio
interior.
Y cada exploración requiere entender las
leyes de cada una de esas realidades.
Y esas leyes no son simples.
Hemos venido estudiando física por dos mil
años,
y siguen apareciendo nuevas capas.
Cada capa que vamos descubriendo nos va
dando una nueva dimensión de la realidad
que nos sigue sorprendiendo.
La promesa es que existen muchos tesoros
adentro de muchos espacios.
Y como cada buscador de tesoros,
está bueno tener un mapa.
Y por supuesto que sea preciso el mapa,
que es mucho mejor que un mapa no preciso.
Al principio como que confiamos en otros.
Y al principio como que queremos tomar
nota para armar nuestro propio mapa.
Y el tema de hoy es el tema de hoy.
Es un mapa bastante rústico de nuestro
mundo interno.
De lo que vamos a atravesar cinco.
Pero ese número es arbitrario.
Estas no son líneas difíciles,
bien delimitadas.
Son como sensaciones que se sobreponen e
interactúan.
Son como una profundización en especial de
tres capas que son las que están más
elevadas, más altas.
Y puede profundizar en cada una de estas
cinco capas.
Y eso es lo que hemos hecho como personas,
como seres humanos.
Hay gente que se siente como distante,
cold.
Ah, un chamago.
Entonces a esas temas que están como
llamados, le dan como una atención
especial.
No quiero olvidarme de decir...
Y si durante esta charla se ven atraídos o
les llama la atención alguna de estas
capas...
Y no han encontrado el llamado que la vida
los llama, o el suadharma...
Entonces estén atentos a si sienten algún
llamado porque eso puede ser algo que les
llame la atención para poder profundizar.
Y no dejen
pasar esa oportunidad, esa posibilidad.
We're going to do a small practice.
Lying down.
I'm going to be asking you to rotate your
awareness in different areas.
There is really nothing else to do.
Even if the translation sometimes has a
pause, don't worry about it.
Just keep listening passively.
Head facing this way, feet facing the
other way.
You're doing great.
Sometimes I lose the beginning.
You want to make your body as straight as
possible in the spine.
Spine as straight as possible.
The feet are hip to shoulder width apart.
Rolling outwards as comfortable.
Palms turned upwards.
Back of the head balanced along the
midline.
Keep checking into your body parts and
find a way to release the weight of them
onto the floor.
If you have any glasses on or anything
tight around the waist or hair,
that can also be removed.
Right at this moment, check into how you
feel physically.
Any body parts that may have been talking
to you or are talking to you right now.
Notice how you feel energetically.
Are you feeling tired and could stay in
this position for the next few hours?
Or feeling energetic and would like to run
a few laps?
Or somewhere in the middle?
When you're with yourself in this state of
stillness, is the mind loud or quiet?
Is it happy to notice what's in the
present moment or is there something it's
going to in the past or future?
There is no judgment either way.
Really be the detached observer.
Are there any deep feelings that you're
aware of carrying inside you?
Any life situations you've recently found
a solution for?
Or that you continue to be challenged by?
And underlying any movements of the breath
or the mind?
Can you contact that part of you that's
always the same?
That part of you that is the essence of
you.
That part of you that even at this moment
silently repeats, I am.
I am here.
I am conscious.
If there is any positive sentence you use
in your life, this is the time to repeat
it mentally.
And if you have any sentence, any prayer,
any positive resolution you use in your
life, this is a good time to repeat it.
Any sentence or prayer that somehow
manifests any deep transformation you want
to achieve.
And if you don't have that sentence,
you can visualize an ideal situation of
yourself.
We are going to move our attention between
the different layers, the different layers
of our being.
And we start with the physical body or
Annamaya Kosha.
And when you hear the name of a part of
the body, bring your attention to that
part.
To remain internally awake, you can
visualize that part and mentally repeat
it.
Awareness in the right hand thumb.
Index finger.
Middle.
Ring.
Little finger.
Palm of right hand.
Back of hand.
Wrist.
Forearm.
Elbow.
Upper arm.
Shoulder.
Armpit.
Right side of torso.
Hip.
Thigh.
Knee.
Shin.
Ankle of right foot.
Heel.
Sole.
Top of foot.
Right foot big toe.
Second toe.
Third.
Fourth.
Fifth toe.
Check that you are internally awake.
Awareness in the left hand thumb.
Index finger.
Middle.
Ring.
Little finger.
Palm of left hand.
Back of hand.
Wrist.
Forearm.
Elbow.
Upper arm.
Shoulder.
Armpit.
Left side of torso.
Hip.
Thigh.
Knee.
Shin.
Ankle of left foot.
Heel.
Sole.
Top of foot.
Left foot big toe.
Second toe.
Third.
Fourth.
Fifth.
Now moving along the back side of the
body.
Touch the mind to the heels.
Calves.
Back of knees.
Back of thighs.
Buttocks.
Lower back.
Middle back.
Upper back.
Shoulder blades.
Space between the shoulder blades.
Back of neck.
Back of head.
The spine from tailbone to back of head.
Crown of head.
Forehead.
Right temple.
Left temple.
Right eyebrow.
Left eyebrow.
Eyebrow center.
Right ear.
Left ear.
Right cheek.
Left cheek.
Nose.
Nariz.
Lips.
Labios.
Jaw.
Mandibula.
Shin.
Mentón.
Throat.
Garganta.
Base of throat.
Right chest.
Left chest.
Chest center.
Upper abdomen.
Navel.
Lower abdomen.
Pubic bone.
Pelvic floor.
Check into your current state of
consciousness.
If the mind has entered sleep,
remain connected to the voice.
Feel into the whole right leg and foot.
The whole left leg and foot.
Both legs and feet.
Right arm and hand.
The whole left arm and hand.
Both arms and hands as one.
Back of torso.
Front of torso.
The whole torso.
Neck.
Head and face.
The neck, head and face together.
Experience the whole right half of the
body.
The whole left half of body.
Experience the whole body at the same
time.
Be aware of which body parts are within
and outside the field of awareness.
And bring awareness into those areas where
it is not.
Deepening into the experience of full body
awareness.
From the inside of the bones to the
surface of the skin.
And now we move into the Pranic dimension.
The Pranamaya Kosha.
Within the stillness of the body,
feel for signs of life.
The beating of the heart and circulation
of blood.
Any digestion and metabolism of energy.
Sensations of warmth or coolness in the
body.
Movements of the natural breath.
With each breath out, follow the breath
from the sternum to out the nasal
passages.
With each breath out, follow the breath
from the sternum to out the nasal
passages.
This is the pathway of Prana, the upward
moving vital force.
Now with each breath in, feel it move from
navel down to pelvic floor.
This is the region of Apana, the downward
moving vital force.
Shift the awareness to the navel and
imagine a side to side movement with each
breath.
Now shift the attention to the navel and
imagine a side to side movement with each
breath.
The region of Samana Prana.
Relaxed body, open mind.
Feeling for anything that feels like the
movement of energy described.
Place the awareness now through the legs
and arms.
The area of Udana, vital force.
Any movements you are aware of through the
legs and arms.
In the form of the subtlest sensation you
are aware of in those regions.
And finally, feel for an energy that
pervades the whole body.
Vyana Prana.
It is the reservoir or buffer vital force.
We
now move our awareness through the parts
of the mind.
Starting with Manas or perception and
cognition.
Become aware of body parts and mind.
Move your attention in contact with the
floor.
Move your mind to the most predominant or
strongest sensation.
Stay there for some time, then find the
next most predominant sensation.
Specifically, sensation of touch.
Now include the top surface of the body as
well.
Continue to move the mind from sensation
to sensation.
We move to Buddhi or the intellect.
Imagine a square.
Place a dot at the center of each line of
that square.
Connect those dots and see what new shape
is revealed.
Connecting only the adjacent dots.
And with this new shape, find the midpoint
of each new line.
And connect those new dots, the adjacent
ones.
Let that go, move into the aspect of
Chitta or memory.
Go back to the moment of waking up this
morning.
Recall the first sensation that woke you
up.
And begin to play through the day up until
this moment now.
The major moments of the day.
Be aware at which points there are gaps
and which points are vivid.
Remain internally aware and awake with
review of the day.
If the mind engages or gets distracted,
come back to the review.
If you finish the review, go back and add
details.
Letting that go, we now move into
Ahamkara.
Imagine that your life is divided into
four parts, your age divided by four.
What were you like in your first stage of
life, in your first quarter?
Your personality, your dreams.
What do you remember about yourself in the
first quarter of life?
That feeling of being you.
Now move into the second quarter of your
life.
What new identity emerged?
How did the views of the world change
based on these new experiences?
Move into the third portion of life.
What was the sense of self at this stage?
Did the personality or self-identity take
new forms?
And finally, what is your idea of yourself
in this current stage of life?
What has been the transformation of the
ego from that first stage?
What aspects of you remain?
What aspects of you have completely
emerged?
Or fallen away?
We now rotate our awareness through the
deep psyche.
Bring the awareness into the region of the
pelvic floor.
Muladhara chakra.
Security and basic needs.
The pelvic region around the base of the
spine and pubic bone.
Joy and fulfillment of karmas.
Healthy sexuality and creativity.
The area of the abdomen around the navel.
Willpower, ego, identity.
The region of the heart around the
sternum.
Community, generosity and deep feeling.
The area around the base of the throat.
Transformation and purification.
The area of the head around the eyebrow
center.
Intuition, wisdom and guidance.
The area at the top of the head.
A sense of total integration between all
other dimensions.
Have a sense of your awareness and state
of consciousness as it is now.
Is it predominantly in any one kosha?
The physical body.
Energetic body.
Mental dimension.
Intuitive or psychic dimension.
Or some subtler aspect of consciousness.
Look into the space behind the forehead,
the mental screen.
Notice anything that may be arising in
that area.
Any color, any darkness or light.
Memories or inner dialogue.
Watch them like clouds, giving them
permission to change and move.
And finally move down into the heart space
around the chest.
Checking in if you feel anything there.
It can be physical sensations or energetic
sensations.
Actual emotions.
Begin to breathe more deeply so you feel
this area of the chest expand and
contract.
Take progressively longer breaths so that
the abdomen is involved as well.
Begin to externalize the senses such as
awareness of sounds.
Sounds from all directions.
Sensations of touch from below and above.
Awareness of smells coming in with each
breath.
Visualize where you are in the room and
features of the room.
And know that this practice has come to an
end.
Begin to bring movements into your fingers
and toes.
Wrists and ankles.
Neck and head.
Give yourself a long stretch like you are
waking up in the morning with a breath in.
Then exhale and hug your knees into your
chest.
Rocking from side to side, massaging the
back.
And over the next minute, find your way
back to sitting.
Keeping your eyes closed if you are
comfortable to do so.
And remain in a state of stillness for a
few moments longer.
In which dimension does your awareness
naturally settle?
Bring the hands into pranam mudra.
Move into a vigorous round of palming.
Trying to make the hands very hot.
And then bringing that heat to the covered
eyes.
Connect with the sensations of pressure
and heat.
Inhale that warmth back into yourself.
And exhaling, lower the hands.
We are going to take a five minute break.
Try and keep it at five minutes if
possible.
And then we will come back to a few spinal
loosening practices and one short
pranayama.
And then go into the more theoretical
concepts.
Okay, stay on still.
We are going to do some standing practices
just to give our spine a break.
If you have never done these practices
before, they will serve you for a
lifetime.
The spine, if you look in yoga,
the spine is the pathway that you find
from Hatha Yoga all the way to Kundalini
Yoga.
So it's used in every single branch from
gross to subtle.
Like that point from earlier, it requires
millions of connections to really get into
a part of ourselves.
I highly recommend as many spinal
awareness practices as you can in your
lifetime.
Because ultimately we want to be able to
follow a single atom from the base all the
way to the brain itself.
Feet together, hands interlaced on top.
Inhale as you stretch upwards and down the
walls.
Exhale, lowering.
Four more times in.
Hold for a few moments.
Exhale.
Three on your own.
Keep the awareness in the spine and on
deep breathing.
When finished, separate the feet out,
shoulder-width apart.
Palms flipped upwards.
Deep breath in.
Exhaling, bend to one side.
Notice what you feel and where you feel
it.
Inhale centered and exhale opposite.
Inhale up, that's one round.
Two out.
In.
Out.
Three more on your own.
If you can, even visualize the bend.
Imagine that your breath is what initiates
movement.
And remain connected to the actual
sensations in the spine.
When you finish the three rounds,
you can lower the hands.
The next round requires the arms being
out.
We're in a tight space.
You can even put your arms around like
you're hugging yourself.
Just don't karate chop your neighbor.
You're going to twist to the left,
pushing on the left shoulder.
Inhale to center.
Exhale, twist to the right, push on the
right.
Inhale, center.
Exhale, left.
Exhale, right.
Inhale, center.
Three more on your own.
When finished, come on the hands and
knees.
We do a few rounds of the cat pose.
If you know it, you can begin,
otherwise we describe one round.
Exhaling, arch up, chin down.
Inhale, curve down, chin up.
Exhaling, round the spine up.
Inhaling, curve down.
Three more on your own.
Don't just do the movements, feel the
movements.
Is there any part of the spine you do not
feel, or that you feel acutely?
When finished with five rounds,
come to sit on the heels if okay for your
knees, otherwise a cross-legged posture.
Hands resting on the thighs or lap.
Awareness at the entrance of the nasal
passages.
By feeling the force coming in and out of
each nostril, estimate which one is
breathing more strongly.
This is called Suara Dominance.
It tends to fluctuate every 60 to 80
minutes.
It is an indicator of which nervous system
is more active.
We are going to use one of the most
beneficial and gentle pranayamas for
bringing it towards balance.
We are going to do one of the simplest and
most elementary pranayamas to achieve a
balance between the two forces.
We are going to imagine inhaling through
the left to eyebrow center,
exhaling down the right,
then inhaling back up the right to eyebrow
center,
exhaling down the left.
So you are always inhaling from one side
but exhaling from the other.
And then inhaling from that other side and
exhaling from the first.
Continue some rounds of alternate nostril
breathing.
This is an ideal pranayama to do between
any transition in the day.
Arriving home from work, preparing to go
to sleep, even waking up in the morning.
The breath is as silent as possible,
at the same time as long and deep as
possible.
So in the same way that you are balancing
the two nostrils,
it is also a balance between effort of
breathing and depth of breathing.
Next time you exhale, start to breathe in
equally from both.
Each breath in merges at the eyebrow
center, each breath out splits and flows
out equally.
Bring the
hands into pranamudra, move into a round
of palming, cover the eyes, gaze into the
darkness.
Inhale deeply into yourself,
exhaling lower the hands and slowly open
the eyes.
I've done two of these talks already in
Montevideo, in different venues,
and of course they change with each time
because they're not really scripted.
And this time I was determined to do a
little bit of practice first.
For those of you who are yoga teachers or
practitioners,
there's always value in hearing something
being done slightly differently.
Especially if you feel like you know the
practice.
It's very easy to slip into a routine
where something works and so you just
deliver it the same forever.
I think that's great, but then we risk
plateauing our own knowledge and how to
engage with those in front of us,
including ourselves.
And for those of you who may not be
familiar with some of these practices,
I think it's harder to find them online
whereas the information is abundant.
It's hard, isn't it?
To find the practices online.
First idea is things that are gross and
things that are subtle.
There's an aspect of reality that's
available to our five senses and there's
an entire aspect of reality that isn't
accessible by our senses.
Or at least our external senses.
And yet most of us would agree that if we
were to suddenly become blind,
we're still a person.
We have a sense of self, right?
So now cut out a secondary sensation.
Now we can't hear as well.
Still a person or not?
What if we cut out all the five external
senses?
Maybe an altered sense of reality,
but we can imagine we'd still have a sense
of...
I'm here, don't kill me, right?
This is a really interesting topic in the
world of coma patients.
Sometimes no real sign of life other than
some brainwave activity.
And yet we've had people come out of
really long comas and say, No,
I was having an inner experience,
I was there.
And all of us experience that even in
states of deep sleep.
We're not there, but through some training
we can progressively develop a sense of,
I'm somewhere.
Even with the physical body, you can start
to cut off limbs, but as long as the
spinal cord, a few vital organs in the
brain are intact, And the same thing
happens with the physical body.
We can remove some parts, amputate,
but leaving behind some important organs,
we still have the sensation of existing.
As if the vital force continues to
maintain a force of consciousness and
vitality, a sensation.
There are yogis who are aware of this,
and when they say yogi, they mean anyone
who has the consciousness to explore the
inner world.
And when he uses the word yoga,
he does not speak exclusively of Indian
thought.
He is preserving and evolving these
aspects of self-exploration.
But yoga and tantra as a search for
universal patterns,
is not distinct to India, and no one has a
claim on it.
So the yogis who observe that you can cut
away aspects of at least these three
layers, So we can cut away the aspects of
these three layers.
Physical to mental.
And removing these layers, we can ask
ourselves, at what point do we stop being
us?
It is very difficult, because no one wants
to die doing this process.
Many people have given up their lives
trying to transmit this.
All of the gurus have sat in between fires
for multiple years.
That practice is known to kill people.
That's one of the last practices for a
number of yogis.
Because it's extreme.
It's extreme physically, it's extreme
energetically, it's extreme mentally.
And the idea is one, is to burn karma
through that austerity.
But the second is, through that stress,
to force oneself into the most subtle
cracks of consciousness.
In the physical dimension, I only listed a
few, but you can imagine that there are
many more.
In the physical dimension, I only listed a
few, but you can imagine that there are
many more.
And he says that all the things that I
have put there, in the physical body,
are superimposed with the energetic part
and with the mental part.
And that the heart, for example,
will not beat, that I'm aware of,
without a functioning brain.
But just entertain me for a moment and
imagine what I mean by physical really
means physical.
Imagine that...
Imagine that the physical part,
for a moment, is only the physical part,
only the physical part of the body.
As if it were the brick of that wall.
So the energetic part is the part that
permeates that physical part.
So it can navigate or dive into that
physical part.
And if you study cell biology and the
biological chemical reactions within,
energy has evolved to both flow
and remain charged like a capacitor.
Even in the wall, there is potential
energy, there is energy within the cement.
There is energy running through the wires
that light up the lights.
And this mental dimension, I invite you to
think of it as the functional mind.
A mind that can be programmed and changed.
Perception, cognition.
A lower intellect, meaning decision
making, pattern recognition.
Memory recollection, memory storage.
And a sense of self that has this idea of,
oh, I am this distinct person.
I have not had the experience of being
confused as someone else.
I'm sure that is possible.
My ego has been healthy in this life to
where I'm contained.
A lot of work is done in the more advanced
branches like bhakti yoga, where there is
the intention to actually dissolve the ego
in order to more universally feel what
everyone is feeling.
That's described as Atma Bhava.
Sometimes in psychic experiences we also
have a sense of shared reality.
But shared ego is more rare as far as I'm
aware.
This here is considered part of the gross
body.
These two, the subtle body, especially in
this area.
A really good example of a subtle body is
the body that you move around in when you
are dreaming.
How many of you remember your dreams?
Maybe half the room, a little more.
How many of you repeatedly remember your
names in your dream?
When's the last time in your dream you
could say definitively, I am Satchitananda
from Nepal?
How many of you could say in your dream,
I am so and so from Tabao?
And think how many times you repeat that
when you are awake in a normal day.
I find it very hard to remember my name in
dreams.
In fact, when I've tried to do so,
I've come up with other names.
That's why it's subtle.
It has unexpected results, it's harder to
access.
Even making a mental body, for some it may
be easy, for me it's really hard.
I have to construct every single part.
And it never looks like this body.
Then we enter a causal area.
And when I say causal, I want you to
consider what that means for you.
I'm going to use the metaphor of the seed.
If you truly know what type of seed
something is, you can predict the tree or
the plant that's going to emerge from it.
The Gyanamaya Kosha contains all the seed
templates in this reality.
The entire physics of the world.
When Newton or the other parallel
discoveries at the same time as him,
discovered all the discoveries that took
place at the time of Newton.
Intuitive gravity.
They found a way to explain a template for
this reality.
Tens of billions of light years.
So that design called gravity seems to be
universally true as far as we know.
Even more interesting to me, any discovery
from this dimension, one of the most
important things is that any discovery
from that dimension, as Wisdom says,
which would be wisdom, knowledge,
seems to be true for the physical and the
psychological dimensions.
Have you ever been in the action zone of
someone you didn't want to be and you
wanted to be?
What is a really good way to do that?
Find someone with a bigger gravity.
This is why gurus have been around for
thousands of years.
If you find your master, they're going to
have a center of gravity that's like a
black hole.
I've seen it thousands of times in the
ashram and in my own life.
It can work for the positive or the
negative.
That's why we all need to have really
heightened sense of our orbits and
influence of others.
That's why we need to be really attentive
to the effects that other people have on
us.
Every physical body has a physical gravity
and every mind has a psychological
gravity.
Buoyancy or the ability to float is
important for lifeguards.
Buoyancy as a tool for remaining positive
is important for our psychological health.
Yet some of us may not have any safety
gear in our lives in the same way that we
have safety gear in a pool.
But in the yogic model, we're all swimming
in the samsaric ocean of life.
So until we learn to swim really,
really well,
it can be very helpful to be mindful of
our surroundings.
It can be very helpful and sometimes
life-saving to have the right equipment
around.
That's what yogic lifestyle and yogic
tools largely is in our first stage of
evolution.
Just like children, when we don't need the
floats anymore, we put on the scuba gear.
And then we can really start to dive into
the depths of these more dangerous or
unknown realms.
I've written down some of the subdivisions
which we did in the Yoga Nidra.
In terms of energy flow, there's like five
major types of prana.
If you study Chinese medicine,
they go into great depth.
Meridians, the energetic quality of food.
Sub-centers in the body.
And how to shift them with lifestyle and
diet and thought.
In the mental dimension, these are the
very rough distinctions of the lower mind.
In the mental body, there are these four
very clear divisions.
You can go into much more detail.
And for Vijnanamaya Kosha, what he
suggests is to use his own terms.
So like patterns, designs, I don't know
how to translate...
So he says that sometimes life becomes
challenging because I disconnect from that
area.
And experience a deep lesson.
Two months later, I'm repeating the
lesson.
So it wasn't as deep as I thought or my
connection wasn't as stable as I hoped.
It was like he had one thing and he said,
I liked what I learned, but two months
later, the same thing happened to him.
How to give more priority or more
attention to that, to Vijnanamaya?
To get out of the cycle of...
...of making mistakes and learning again.
He says that this is the most attractive
part of the patterns and designs,
the most attractive part of that part,
of that body.
As it comes out of the individual being
and we begin to access more universal
knowledge.
The formulas of gravity did not exist
until we intuitively began to imagine that
there was something.
The force existed, right?
And so that one has to ask themselves,
well, if knowledge can be accessed
directly, how do I encourage that so I
don't reach the same conclusion through
trial and error?
Does that make sense?
Because that would save a lot of time and
energy within a lifespan.
This is why we always start with awareness
at the eyebrow center.
Why?
Why the eyebrow center?
Because it's the claim that that center
awakens intuition.
And why are we always doing that at the
beginning and ending of every practice?
Anyone?
Because it requires millions of
connections repeatedly to stabilize a
connection.
So if you look at the yogic practices,
those things that are the most significant
will be seeded everywhere throughout a
practice.
So if you look at the yogic practices,
those things that are the most significant
will be seeded everywhere throughout a
practice.
The mantra OM.
The mantra SHANTI.
Sankalpa.
Sankalpa is an act of willpower.
If you put your hand on your leg and try
and lift it,
you can only explain how that was achieved
to a certain point that I'm aware of.
At some level of explanation, something
happens within that says, I will lift my
hand.
Yes, the biology supports the movement.
Yes, energy is required to work against
gravity.
Yes, the nervous system has to be intact
between hand and brain.
Yes, movement has to be possible.
But ultimately, something within you,
aside from a reflex,
has to give consent to that action.
This is called Icha Shakti.
The desire for something to happen.
Science calls it Big Bang for our current
physical reality.
The esoteric explanation is an act of Icha
Shakti.
Somewhere in the causal field,
before time, there was an impulse to be.
And now we have the tangible reality.
But we're not disconnected from that
initial action of 13 billion years ago.
We can't be logically.
Otherwise we wouldn't be here looking at
each other.
It's like asking, where is the beginning
and end of a river?
There isn't one.
It's all ocean, sky, river.
The divisions are utilitarian.
But the reality is more continuous.
So,
if there is the interest to know how far
back we can reach into ourselves,
that will always pull us back to the
causal dimension.
All of this will end up bringing us back
to the causal dimension.
So, most of these layers that we can
contact at the same time will give us the
feeling of stability and integrity.
Because all of these are like a part of
who we are.
And one of his main actors is Jim Carrey.
And Jim Carrey said that depression is
like the soul asking for change.
At the time of COVID, he says that there
was a very strong depression.
Ah, he says that he was in his peak
physical health.
He had the training of two German
shepherds.
He managed all the computer systems of the
ashram.
But totally ignoring these two dimensions.
Which left me with a table with three
working legs.
And as soon as I started to feel more
pressure on this leg,
I found that the whole system collapsed.
And in that discovery of how that happened
and how to get out of it, I came across a
lot of students who were going through
similar things.
And in each case, one of these four tended
to be lacking.
Or in other words, undernourished.
And that's why we started out with
Shantipat, rotation through the five
koshas.
Yoga Nidra, rotation through the five
And the Satyananda Yoga recommendation for
the day.
To do practices for each of the koshas,
small amounts, throughout the day.
Because it really does require that
real-time assessment of the health of each
of these dimensions.
Porque requiere como un chequeo diario de
esas cuatro dimensiones.
Porque no hay que dejar ignorado a uno de
esas cuatro dimensiones por un periodo
largo.
Some of us are really good at balancing on
two legs.
As long as life doesn't throw anything too
unexpected at us.
And sometimes we see very stable people
crumble under circumstances that's hard to
understand why.
En situaciones que son sencillas,
digamos simples.
Y vamos a ignorar la dimensión causal por
un momento.
No soy un artista.
Dicen que en mi época dibujo mejor que
esto.
There is a practice called SWAN.
Strength, weakness, ambitions and needs.
And one way to use that is with the
koshas.
You write down all your physical strengths
and weaknesses.
Todas las fortalezas y debilidades a nivel
físico.
Entonces sabe por experiencia que su
cuello es una de las partes más flojas de
su cuerpo.
Número dos, la espalda baja.
Y la tercera, las rodillas.
Cuando hace su práctica diaria le aprecia
esas tres áreas.
Energéticamente tiene alguna idea de lo
que agota sus pranas.
Y lo que lo recarga.
Cuando se olvida de eso es como que se
siente sin energía, cansado, agotado.
Lo mismo para la dimensión mental.
Fumaba mucha marihuana de chico.
La memoria de corto plazo realmente le dio
un golpe.
Y así sé lo que es bueno para mí es la
revisión del día.
La revisión del día es una de las
prácticas más potentes para recuperar la
memoria de corto plazo y desarrollar
visualización.
Si tienen padres como ya mayores o conocen
niños a los que les cuesta enfocarse,
busquen formas sencillas y naturales de
visualizar la memoria de corto plazo y
desarrollar visualización.
Yo era tanto profesor en la escuela de
alta escuela, como abogado por años,
y trabajaba con personas que estaban en el
camino a la muerte.
Cada grupo beneficia y parece disfrutar de
revisar lo que han justo experimentado en
un día o en una vida.
Durante el día o durante la vida.
Entonces, a través de estas prácticas uno
empieza a darse cuenta del largo de sus
piernas.
Y claro, después nos damos cuenta de que
están como a distintos niveles,
entonces, ¿qué pasa si ponemos un tacho de
sopa arriba?
Es una mesa insegura.
And sometimes in life we put things on our
table, which we are going to call life,
and we achieve, place, and we lose.
It can be the loss of relationships that
are significant to us.
It can be the loss of happiness that was
promised by a job or an object.
In all cases, I think, that tends to roll
off the leg that's the shortest.
It's not even the case that these legs
have to be so long.
They just have to be balanced relatively.
They just have to be medium or well
balanced, balanced.
And sometimes all the legs are there,
but they are weak, weak.
We don't have time to get into that in
this session, but it's what would be the
part of the Gunas.
It's the quality of what we bring into our
lives as structures.
And because we are out of time,
the last thing I want to say is,
knowing that these are not individual and
isolated,
to take time to inspect every life
experience,
mundane to profound, mundane, like very
normal, to profound, and map out how many
different koshas are involved in that
experience.
Sleep, for example, involves all of the
koshas.
You know that we have found that even life
forms without spinal cords display sleep.
Life forms without nervous systems,
like jellyfish.
have observable sleep states.
To me that's really interesting.
Because it implies it comes from a deeper
area than just biology.
Even modern scientists say this is not the
first Big Bang.
Which means there's a point at rest
between manifest and unmanifest,
where all of everything is just rest.
This is the creation story of Vishnu in
the scriptures.
He's in a state of Yoga Nidra until the
idea comes, Oh, let's enjoy a creation
again.
Different explanations for the same
phenomenon.
Relationship dysfunction.
I use this just as an example because it's
been coming up in a lot of friends,
friends and family.
Partners who have trouble connecting
physically or emotionally.
But there's no checklist of what can we do
together in these different koshas to
start building a connection again.
It's hard to imagine that you're going to
repair sexual distance if you can't hug
someone and really enjoy that hug.
Or have a deep talk with your son or
daughter if you can't even talk about the
day with a real sense of interest.
And so that's the way I've started to use
the koshas as a map in my life.
To have them actually laid out in front of
me.
And when I experience an imbalance,
which is daily, usually by 9 a.m.,
then it's become a really fun process to
say in which multiple koshas is this
connected to.
And that's always shifting because we are
dynamic field entities.
I'm challenging your Spanish.
We're almost done.
It's the last minute.
We're beings that are actually dynamic
fields.
That's all the ideas I could get out with
the time allotted today.
That's mostly what I had in my notes.
I have transcripts and if you fill out the
feedback form, I'll send you the notes to
the past two talks as well.
Yeah,
I'll send it to you.
And I know an hour or two hour talk,
it's a lot of ideas.
I really hope you take some time to read
back through this in your own way,
using your own resources.
Create your own version of this map.
And then give me some feedback.
In time, it's so enriching to hear someone
else's model of moving through themselves.
No matter what you're engaged in life.
I believe if you put some attention to
these five koshas before you begin,
it's going to enhance whatever you're
doing.
Hari Om Tat Sat.
We're going to end it there.
You can mentally repeat Om Shanti with me.
And we went over time by 15 minutes.
If you have somewhere to be, please don't
speed.
And otherwise, take care.
Thank you very much for your time.
Thank you.