Hello.
Hey, Luis.
Can we move the table because of the zoom,
the camera?
So it can appear this or you don't need to
appear this?
I don't have to appear.
No?
It's okay?
It's okay.
As long as my voice appears.
What do you think?
Yes, it's okay.
How far in do I have to go?
No, that's okay.
That's good.
Am I in now?
Yeah, now.
Oh, that's cool.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
Okay.
That's better.
Better?
Yeah.
I think that if you come here...
Yeah, that's right.
It's okay?
Yeah, that's okay.
Great.
Yeah.
Maintaining there this attitude of
reception, we are going to talk a little
about the mistakes we made in this
program.
The first mistake was that we didn't
present it as a retreat.
It's a retreat that starts tomorrow,
from 6 in the morning, and ends on Tuesday
afternoon.
But we were interested in promoting the
people who are going to participate in
this retreat, mainly Vanessa Chidananda,
who comes from Nepal, who is going to be
guiding a thread in this retreat.
The thread is going to be linked...
on the first day, it's going to be linked
to the physical body, then the body to the
breathing part, the environment,
and then we are going to have an
experience.
So, we are going to make up for that
mistake in the end, there is going to be a
thread in which you can take all the
information and decide if you want to
participate in this retreat, or a day,
a day from 8 in the morning until 7 p.m.,
or only a special activity.
These special activities are led by
several local people from Dubai who
contribute to what Vanessa Chidananda
wanted to do, to make this sequence of
events.
So, you decide, you will choose the format
you want to do.
This is the introduction talk,
and we want to thank Maka for having
received us this second time, because the
first time we filled the room,
and this time too, so that's why they
invite us.
In addition to the theme we want to thank
Leonardo from Argentina.
We invite you to get to know Yoga 104,
we are neighbors here.
Instead of seeing the wide area of 5.5
meters, we have 5.7 meters.
Instead of talking to the left,
we talk to the right, and this is Yoga
104.
So, welcome, and welcome Vanessa
Chidananda.
We light up with something that last year,
we were already advanced.
Last year, after this meeting,
we had a small meeting of people who
approached and mentioned Claude.
Today, Claude is on all the pages,
constantly infiltrating all this
artificial intelligence.
Already at that moment, he trained us to
begin to discover this new world that is
coming, and we believe that there is no
way to stop it.
We followed the press, we followed the
industrial revolution, we followed the
digital revolution, and we are moving
backwards.
So, let's take advantage of this,
advantage of people who know they are
involved in this, as many of you know,
to advance in this digital world.
Welcome everyone.
Thank you.
Namaste and Hari Om to everyone.
Thank you for your presence here tonight.
Hari Om.
Namaste.
Greetings to everyone.
And I want to start by thanking the
museum, of course, for having me back
here.
I was here last year as well.
And to Yoga 104, which holds many
different types of programs.
And to lastly express gratitude to all the
traditions, to all the masters,
to all the sources of knowledge that have
come into my life.
I want to thank all the sources of
knowledge, to all the masters who have
contributed all this information to my
life.
I think this museum is one of the most
suitable places to have discussions about
consciousness and technology.
Because we can see in this amazing space
that it's a blend of both.
Art, in particular, seems to have an
amazing quality or ability
to highlight and reveal layers of our
shared reality that we might not otherwise
pay attention to.
Even just walking through the museum
today, I'm coming across exhibits that
highlight various parts of myself.
The intention for sharing the idea of
koshas, or the layers of our body,
is to invite you to see the world in a way
that you may not already be experiencing
it.
Whether you believe we live once or
thousands of lives,
it would be ideal to live every life to
the fullest.
Most of us agree with that statement.
But what does it actually mean to be full?
We understand that in the context of a
bathtub.
Because it has boundaries.
But what if our boundaries aren't limited
to matter or our physical body?
Then what does it mean to be full in the
next dimension of our being, if there is
one?
And so we go into a very short and small
journey into these layers
that have been searched for for over
thousands of years.
What I share is the discovery of more than
one culture.
But it's not the end of discovering.
We have not reached the final layer.
And this is where modalities such as yoga
come in.
And this is why spaces such as Yoga 104
exist.
To let us be our own explorers and not
just blindly trust what has been told to
us.
If any of the ideas tonight are new or
resonate with you,
I sincerely invite you to explore it to
its end
and find a way to let me know what your
experience was.
I'm going to start by asking you to really
make yourselves very comfortable in your
chair.
You might already be walking in here with
a certain pattern of holding yourself,
conditioned by years or decades of moving
in the physical world.
Close your eyes for a moment.
Push your backs up against the seat.
Allow your arms to relax on your thighs or
knees or arm rests.
Allow the legs to be symmetrical,
the feet to be well supported by the
floor.
And see if you can arrange the left half
of the body so that it mirrors the right
half exactly.
If you've taken the invitation to close
your eyes, imagine yourself seated as you
are.
Feel the weight of your body,
the different parts of your body,
including the inner organs, muscles and
bones, skin, hair and nails.
At any point, feel free to open your eyes
should you choose to.
Otherwise, feel free to keep them closed.
Your awareness is currently in the
Annamaya Kosha, the physical body.
Anna means food in Sanskrit.
That part of us which is constructed by
the food we eat, that is considered the
physical body.
It has a very deep intelligence of its
own.
It's extremely strong and extremely
vulnerable at the same time.
Next, I want you to connect with your
breathing.
The moment that it enters your nasal
passages to the point that it actually
fills your lungs.
And follow that same breath all the way
out the body.
With each new breath, see if you can make
it a little bit longer, a little bit
deeper.
The body without this breath is simply a
corpse.
But as soon as oxygen enters, all of a
sudden there is vitality.
We call this vitality Prana.
It's the life force that has been around
far before earth was even here.
It's the Shakti or energy that is revealed
when matter is exploded.
When we add Prana to a system,
all of a sudden it has the ability to move
matter.
So you can imagine that you are a puppet
at this stage.
And so the question arises, well,
what is it that is moving the strings of
this puppet?
And for this I want you to place your
awareness in your mental faculty,
your ability to hear my words,
to think about what I'm saying,
to be aware of the passing of time,
how much of the way that you think and
receive my words is conditioned by your
culture, how much of it is conditioned by
your gender,
or by your age, or by your stage in life
right now.
At this point we are like robots,
very capable, programmed machines,
like the best cars in the world able to
survive for decades,
able to live for decades.
Yeah, cars.
And able to help navigate us through the
world.
Go one level deeper still and notice what
feelings you're experiencing right now.
The actual emotions,
boredom, interest, curiosity, confusion,
fatigue, calm.
I believe this is the level that actually
makes us human, uniquely human.
What happens what at the moment seems to
differentiate us from the machines that we
have created in our own image.
And finally, the last layer.
I want you to go to that moment of waking
every morning.
Before you have any awareness of where you
are,
before you even recall your name,
it is a fleeting moment that for many of
us passes day by day unexperienced.
And yet, out of that totally unconscious
moment, our life begins again.
Feel free to open your eyes at this point.
What we just traveled through are called
the five koshas,
or the five yogic bodies.
They come from trying to find our limits
of what we can do as a human.
I think right now the Winter Games are
going on, the Winter Olympic Games.
So you have a number of humans who have
spent pretty much their whole lives trying
to find the limits of how well they can
perform.
And there you are going to find many
people who have spent their whole lives
trying to find their limits.
What I find amazing and inspiring,
and much of the rest of the world does as
well, is that we don't seem to have a
limit.
Every time a world record is broken,
every other athlete catches up to that
record.
And then some years later, another athlete
pushes that boundary farther.
And what was unachievable for some number
of years, all of a sudden, all the new
athletes are able to meet that.
Because at that time it was not accessible
for all athletes, everyone can reach that
level.
As part of this talk about technology and
AI, I want to give information about how
each of our five bodies
have been influenced by modern technology.
At the moment, there are monks who are
training with robots.
Kung Fu masters used to be depicted as
wise old men.
Now they are machines developed by Boston
Robotics.
We also have CRISPR, the very advanced
gene editing program,
which continues to evolve and will
definitely get to the point where you can
design your own body.
Some people are already designing the
qualities of their babies.
What does this say about being human when
our looks and feels are totally
changeable?
How does that make you feel about your own
body if you were to live in a time where
you could change anything you wanted about
yourself?
What would you keep the same and what
would you be open to modifying?
And what would influence that decision?
How many of you change your profile
pictures at least once a year?
I only saw one hand up, I don't believe
it.
So how many times a year would you be
willing to change your entire appearance
if that was possible?
The next layer is this energetic
dimension.
The Pranamaya Kosha.
Similar to feats of athleticism,
we continue to break records in the field
of energy.
Certainly in the external world with
energy harnessing.
Energy unpacking with fusion.
But even in the human realm for things
such as how deep can someone dive?
How far can someone run without eating or
sleeping?
We now have watches that tell us how fast
we're breathing.
Our heartbeat.
Our sleep cycles.
And so for the first time I'm aware
technology is starting to regulate our own
energy systems.
And then we get into one of the most
interesting dimensions the Manomaya Kosha
or that of the mind.
Especially those of us in modern countries
and developed countries we seem to be
almost exclusively here.
Far less people are growing their own food
or collecting their own water.
Many of us seek artificial ways of
remaining strong because our lifestyle has
shifted to interior environments.
I come from a country where I don't
believe the things that I'm seeing.
I was in a village where a creek was
covered with a large rock as the bridge.
And I asked the villagers how many people
did it take to lift that single stone?
It was a single stone bridge.
And they said, oh, just one.
And for me it was like hearing something
in the matrix like, no way, that's totally
impossible.
I still don't believe it to this day.
But they said the time when that bridge
was built not one person was that strong,
multiple people in the village.
In the case of the mind, we've definitely
come to a time where we've outsourced
almost all our mental faculties.
The new generation are entering a time
where education has many challenging
questions or problems for them.
Do we teach new people to actually write?
Should we?
Is personal memory actually important when
we have almost infinite memory in most of
our pockets?
What is the value in training our eyes or
ears or nose or tongue or skin to perceive
the world when devices can do it a hundred
times better?
We're also in the age of brain computer
interfaces.
Chips that connect directly to the spinal
cord.
Right now they're in their infant stage,
but one can imagine that in a few years
they will be as powerful as our phones or
computers.
We have technology that can now read
images that are in people's minds and hear
the inner speech that they're speaking.
Colorado, one of the states in the U.S.,
has already passed a law saying it's
illegal to spy on another person's brain.
That's in preparation for technology that
already exists in laboratories that allows
us to do that.
The purpose of giving these examples isn't
to glorify technology
or to present it in a frightening manner.
It's simply to highlight that what we used
to think was uniquely human
is proving to not be uniquely human.
So is there anything about us that makes
us us, that can't be replicated?
And that has been an open question for as
long as humans have been able to think.
And that brings us to this fourth
dimension.
The Vijnanamaya Kosha.
It is the psyche including emotions,
the space of intuition and what we call
wisdom.
And I think it's helpful to think of it as
the space of all knowledge,
of anything that can be known,
of the underlying order of this reality.
And the underlying chaos.
Many of the greatest discoveries in the
world came not from the mind but from the
intuition of very deep souls.
These include poets, artists of all types,
scientists.
In the yogic system the capacity of what
we can feel starts at the base of the
spine and goes to the mid of the brain.
It includes everything from fear and
security to love and generosity
to intuition and just knowing things that
defy logic or calculation.
We used to feel very confident that this
was a dimension that technology could not
really enter
because it included things as unique as
love.
But now people have AI partners that they
are truly in love with.
We have a growing number of people that
use chatbots as effective therapists
rather than humans.
And we're certainly at the point where if
any of us had a conversation with a
personality we could not see we could not
say if it was human or not.
So where does that leave us in terms of
uniqueness and what it means to still be
human now that most of these dimensions
are being simulated.
We have one final one that the yogis have
identified.
The Anandamaya Kosha.
Some say it is pure consciousness.
Undifferentiated awareness.
And many other abstract ideas that I'm not
even trying to really understand because
it feels so subtle.
But if you asked me do I have this I would
say emphatically I do, I'm conscious.
And depending on which AI you ask,
some will say I'm not and others will say
I am.
To me it's less important whether AI is
conscious or not.
And more significant if I am a medium of
consciousness
how do I become the clearest medium
possible for it.
From that perspective the emotional body
or the intuitive body is a container,
an instrument.
The mind is a conduit, an instrument.
The pranic system, the nervous system is a
medium, an instrument.
And the body is certainly just a way to
move around, another instrument.
From this line of thought these cultures
where yogis have made a science of
consciousness, they ask us for thousands
of years, not recently,
to not be overly identified with one's own
body.
It can change, it doesn't have to define
who we are.
That's very liberating, especially because
all of us change from age very young to
very old.
And in those moments where we overly
identify with the body, we tend to
experience some unpleasant feelings when
it changes in a direction we don't like.
And yet changes in the body don't have to
define our sense of vitality,
or our mental capacity, or our ability to
feel deeply and profoundly.
Or to feel that we are part of a greater
reality and not an isolated being.
But even the energetic body is just
another layer.
We have people in hospitals right now that
are in years long coma.
The heart would not pump if it were not
for a machine pumping it.
The lungs would not breathe if it wasn't
for a machine breathing it.
All of their prana is externally supplied.
And it's all seen externally.
And those who come back from a coma can
often tell us about their experiences and
what they have done proving that they were
still there, whatever that they is.
All of us will experience increasingly
diminished energy as we approach death.
But most of us would vote no to a law that
says when someone is below this threshold
they are no longer human.
Cut them off.
But we would never vote for a law in which
all those who are below this level of
energy are eliminated and taken out.
as long as a human can feel,
whether they are a slow thinker or a fast
thinker, an articulate speaker or an
inarticulate speaker,
there is tolerance as humans for each
other and our mindsets.
And so the yogic cultures have said do not
over identify with the mind.
You are not the mind.
It is an instrument for expressing
something deeper.
And then we finally get into this layer of
psyche and emotions and knowledge.
And we find that even this dimension is
changing throughout life.
That even this dimension can be heavily
conditioned.
But it can also be deconditioned.
And this is where a lot of the work of
spiritual modality comes in.
That as we begin to decondition this
layer,
how does that change the way we perceive
the world?
How does it change the quality and the
quantity of vitality we have for wanting
to live in the world?
And how does it change the way that we use
our body, possibly not just as our
identity but as instruments for service?
And so that in short is the end of our
journey.
From physical to energetic, mental and
intuitive or psychic to the causal
dimension.
This is a QR code for the activities that
are happening this week just up the road.
We've designed it so that each day focuses
on one dimension in particular.
And a very special time with Carnival
going on right now.
We have an event called Shivaratri
happening from Saturday night through
Sunday night.
Where everyone is invited to come sing for
up to 24 hours.
If you have never tried to sing for 24
hours it's really challenging.
But not for the reasons you might think.
For many of us who have done it a certain
amount of positivity starts to generate.
And it can actually be challenging to feel
like you're still in your body.
So we'll have other practices throughout
the 24 hours to remain grounded.
Which include eating and guided resting.
But sincerely if you have the opportunity
come by anytime, clap a little bit,
dance a little bit.
And if you know how to sing, sing a little
bit.
And with this museum being close it's an
ideal time to have a back and forth
experience.
Walk through these grounds.
Do some practice that changes the internal
perception.
And then walk through these grounds again
and see if you take in the exhibits in a
different way.
And if you do have that shift in
experience, then something has been
revealed to you.
And it's left to you to figure out what
that quality is.
So, Hari Om Tat Sat and thank you for your
participation and attention.
We're going to continue outside to the
lawn area now.
And do a few practices connected to each
of these dimensions.
If you have the time, come join us for the
next 30 to 45 minutes.
Thank you very much.