The lyrics say, Jai Durga Lakshmi
Saraswati.
Well, now we are going to sing.
Jai Durga Lakshmi Saraswati Jaya Jaya Ambe
Bhavani Ma Jaya Jagad Ambe Bhavani Jai
Durga Lakshmi Saraswati Jaya Jaya Ambe
Bhavani Maa Jaya Jagad Ambe Bhavani Jai
Durga Lakshmi Saraswati Jaya jaya ambe
bhavani Ma jaya jagad ambe bhavani Jaya
jaya ambe bhavani Ma jaya jagad ambe
bhavani Jaya Jaya Ambe Bhavani Maa Jaya
Jagad Ambe Bhavani Jaya Jaya Ambe Bhavani
Maa Jaya Jagad Ambe Bhavani Jaya Jaya Ambe
Bhavani Maa Jaya Jagad Ambe Bhavani Jai
Durga Lakshmi Saraswati Jaya Jaya Ambe
Bhavani Maa MA JAYA JAGAD AMBE BHAVANI DEH
PURGALASHNI SARASWATI JAYA JAYA AMBE
BHAVANI MA JAYA JAGAD AMBE BHAVANI JAYA
JAYA AMBE BHAVANI
Jaya Jaya Ambe Bhavani Ma Jaya Jagadambe
Bhavani
Jaya Jaya Ambe Vavani Ma Jaya Jagad Ambe
Vavani Jaya
Jaya Saraswati Jaya Jaya Ambe Vavani Ma
Jaya Jagad Ambe Vavani Jai Durga Vashni
Saraswati Jaya Jaya Ambe Bhavani Maa Jaya
Jagad Ambe Bhavani
I want to welcome you all.
How, what's comfortable for you for length
of speech?
Not very long.
Good.
A little bit longer than that,
I can manage.
I want to welcome you all and to thank Ram
Navami for hosting me and helping organize
in Chittarupa for supporting my visit and
for translating.
And of course all of you for taking some
interest in the topic and being present
here.
And of course to the gurus of our
tradition living and in the past who bring
us the vidya.
I always like to put a few disclaimers in
front just so there's clarity about who I
am and what I'm talking about.
I am a yoga sadhak, ever more increasingly
interested and sincere.
I am not a Sanskrit scholar or even near
that.
But I've been listening and chanting,
especially this chant, for over a decade
now.
And finally the desire to understand with
more clarity what I'm actually chanting
has started to sprout.
I use technology to help me in that
regard.
And so the resources that have been
prepared is in collaboration with
technology, specifically AI.
And just like working with people,
errors appear.
I try and catch them.
But what I've shared with you,
please do not take as a definitive
reference.
We'll go ahead and start with Shantipat.
So please arrange yourself into any
comfortable asana.
Creating stability through the positioning
of the legs and the buttocks.
A balanced platform for having the spine
comfortably upright.
The neck and head balanced on the
shoulders.
And the hands in a mudra or gesture of
your choice.
You're invited to close the mouth and the
eyes as well.
And to bring yourself into this space.
By connecting to all the sensations you're
experiencing right now.
Start with sensations from the external
environment.
This can include smells and variations in
light.
Sensations felt by the body and sounds as
well.
Allow yourself to be the observer of this
experience.
Noticing any thoughts or feelings that may
arise from connecting with the senses more
deeply.
Sometimes when we focus the mind,
we become aware of what distracts it even
more.
These distractions are also welcome in
this self-awareness.
Find your breath and once you've contacted
it, start to deepen it both directions.
Progressively, so that over a number of
breaths it easily lengthens and slows
down.
With the next breath in, guide the
awareness to the eyebrow center and hold
the focus there.
The eyes can be turned inwards and
slightly upwards to look at that point
from the inside.
Imagine that you're gazing intently at a
bright point of light in the form of a
flame.
Use memory or imagination to try and bring
that idea to light.
With our awareness on that light,
we will chant the mantra OM three times
together and the shanti mantras together
as well.
Take a slow, full breath in to chant the
mantra OM.
Hands
in pranam mudra, moving to a round of
palming.
Once you have some heat or warmth to
share, cover the closed eyes.
Look into that darkened space.
Then inhale that prana into the eyes,
into yourself.
Exhaling, you can lower the hands.
We recently finished a wonderful five days
at Yoga 104.
It was an experiential conference covering
a kosha each day.
And we had different speakers that had
some experience with that kosha for each
day as well.
For example, the first day on the physical
body, we asked someone who had cut into
physical bodies and autopsies.
For the prana day, we had someone who was
an expert in tai chi and working with the
inner energy.
For the mind, someone who had worked with
autism in children for many years and
discovered things about their unique
mental state.
For the intuitive and psychic body,
we had 24 hours of singing on shivaratri.
If you've never tried that, I think we're
going to try and repeat 12 to 24 hours
next year.
Please come.
Usually we stay awake because we have work
to finish or an exam.
And singing out of joy for 24 hours
provides a positive samskara to staying up
all night.
If you look at all the branches of yoga,
they have techniques for providing
positive experiences to negative
samskaras.
And on the fifth day, we had a speaker who
had worked with cancer patients saying,
cancer does not touch the spirit.
Because shivaratri was the peak
experience, a lot of emphasis was around
this idea of consciousness.
And the idea of subtlety in reality.
But in every case, the speakers would
always come back to the body as where we
experience being human.
And it's in this manifest, tangible
reality that we contact shakti.
It's her domain, she creates this reality.
From the tantric perspective or the shakti
tantric perspective, anything we can
experience is her in some form.
And so there are a number of chants that
try and describe her.
The rishis and yogis who intuited these
verses tried to find ways for us to
experience that energy in a real way.
And from the tantric perspective,
to remind us that she is not only the
positive, good, bright rainbow.
She can also be the dark, heavy,
unpleasant, destructive.
And we all have that experience at home
daily.
If you keep filling the trash without
emptying it, your house is going to stink.
If you keep filling the toilet without
flushing, your bathroom is going to stink.
And so shakti creates, but she also
destroys.
And throughout she is maintaining and
transforming.
The suktam that we are going to look at
today talks about that.
The various forms that she takes in our
consciousness.
I had learned this chant, or first learned
it, in the Bihar School of Yoga.
During that course we were taken to
Rikyapit ashram,
where the Satchandi Maha Yajna was taking
place, and it included this chant.
The Satchandi Maha Yajna is five days of
shakti awareness and worship.
It includes the daily repetition of some
chants that describe wonderful stories
about Durga and other forms of the
goddess.
If you or your partner or your children
enjoy modern day superhero films,
you will absolutely enjoy these stories.
They are bloody, they are supernatural,
and they are ultra vivid.
And they have very deep archetypal plot
lines.
I guarantee you will see yourself or one
of your life challenges in every single
story from the Satchandi.
And this is where a lot of value of taking
the time to understand the old languages
comes in.
Because they were recorded and preserved
not for posterity or religious value,
but for our evolution and stability in
life.
This Suktam is particularly accessible.
Because almost all the verses follow the
same pattern.
So once you learn the pattern,
you are just putting in a few filler
words.
And those filler words are different forms
of consciousness that shakti takes.
So I learned this chant in the ashram,
and then I came to my grandparents' house
in Nepal.
And I made a commitment to live with them
for about three years,
knowing that they were probably in the
last years of their life.
My grandfather was a Sanskrit scholar and
practicing tantric Hindu and astrologer.
And an astrologer and practicing Hindu.
And one day, by chance, as someone who
never wakes up to go to the bathroom at
night, I got up to go to the bathroom.
And I heard my grandmother chanting one of
the verses from this Suktam in the middle
of the night.
I listened for about a minute,
took care of myself and went back to bed.
In the morning, I said, I recognize the
verse that you are chanting.
And she was a bit of a cheeky personality,
and she said, yeah, you and everyone else
in this country knows these verses.
Which is something I didn't even realize
that it was a widely known chant.
The particular verse was, Hey Devi,
I call you in the form of sleep,
or I see you in the form of sleep.
I pray to you, I salute you, I respect
you.
She had been experiencing a moment of
insomnia, and she asked my grandmother,
Hey grandfather, what can I do to fall
back asleep?
And he replied, you know how to call her
in the form of sleep, just repeat that
mantra.
And that was a very deep teaching to me
for applied Tantra.
That these mantras are recipes and
invocations for energies that are able to
take form in us.
For hundreds of thousands of years of our
evolution, Prakriti has automated that
process.
The Yogic, the Vedic and the Tantric
cultures have tried to awaken that and
bring it under our conscious control.
Hatha Yoga aims to bring conscious control
over the autonomic nervous system.
Raja Yoga has techniques for bringing
conscious control over deeply embedded
subconscious programming.
Kundalini Yoga or Kriya Yoga brings
awareness into the very subtle psychic
energies.
And mantras give us a very accessible way
to start generating internal waves of
consciousness.
Internal experiences that are normally
dictated by food consumption rhythms,
our food timings,
or the rhythms of the day and night.
And so we break free of these natural
rhythms and take control if we need to.
What I'd like to do is to first listen to
a version recorded by the ashram.
And you're invited to follow along.
It takes about ten minutes.
And then we will go through each of the
verses with more detailed pronunciation.
At which time you're welcome to ask to
repeat a word as often as you like.
And at the same time we'll also look at
the translation so that we know what we're
invoking.
This recording starts out with a short
satsang by Swamiji in English.
Because this chant is often done during
Shakti sadhanas like Navaratri.
We won't translate it today, but if you're
interested just let me know and I'll get
those words to you.
Does anyone not have a copy that needs
one?
Does anyone not have a copy of the sutta?
The power of Saraswati is to give you
wisdom, understanding, appreciation of the
beauty of life.
And the Tamasic power is Durga.
Tamasic does not mean negative here.
Tamasic means, in this context,
something which has to change in order for
something new to come.
So the conditioning which is there,
the existing conditioning has to be
changed, altered, destroyed.
And to change the existing, we need the
power of Durga and that is our sankalp
shakti.
You can sing along if you would like,
quietly.
Satsang with Mooji
Satsang with Mooji Tiruvannamalai,
India
Tiruvannamalai, India
Tiruvannamalai, India Tiruvannamalai,
India Tiruvannamalai, India
Tiruvannamalai, India Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva Bhuteshu,
Yadirupena Samsthita Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva Bhuteshu,
Yadirupena Samsthita Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva Bhuteshu,
Yadirupena Samsthita Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva Bhuteshu,
Yadirupena Samsthita Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva
Bhuteshu, Yadirupena Samsthita Namaskar
Siena, Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva
Bhuteshu, Yadirupena Samsthita Namaskar
Siena, Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva Bhuteshu,
Smriti Rupena Samsthita Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva Bhuteshu,
Yadirupena Samsthita Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva Bhuteshu,
Smriti Rupena Samsthita Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva Bhuteshu,
Smriti Rupena Samsthita Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Yaderi Sarva Bhuteshu,
Yadirupena Samsthita Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Indriana Madhvishparati,
Bhutanam Chahileshu Ya Bhuteshu Satatam
Gase, Yadidevye Namo Namaha Chittirupena
Yadrishna, Veda Vyagya Sthitajagai
Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Om Namaha Namaskar Siena,
Om Namaha Namaskar Siena, Namaskar Siena,
Namaskar Siena, Om Namaha
Is this the first time anyone has ever
heard this Suktam?
Any way you would describe it,
it doesn't have to be positive,
I'm not looking for answers, I'm sincerely
asking.
Would you describe it in any way?
We are not expecting you to say anything
positive, but something sincere.
Sweet.
Soft.
Powerful.
I find even without knowing the meaning,
many chants have their own energetic
quality.
Heavy metal has its quality.
Classical music has its quality.
And this type of Mangpada chanting,
especially Devi chanting, I find has a
unique quality.
And if you ever feel something,
please know that there is an archive of
Shakti chants available online.
And if you ever feel something,
please know that there is an archive of
Shakti chants available online.
YouTube has hundreds of thousands.
But SatyamYogaPrasad.net has a very
careful selection.
Swami Satyananda was a sensational DJ.
I have shown this book to a lot of my
family members in Nepal.
And they always say the equivalent of,
I want that playlist.
And that's when I realized, he was just
really ahead of his time in terms of
compiling really, really good tracks for
the body, heart and mind.
So if you like the track, you might like
the album.
That's on SatyamYogaPrasad.net Alright,
so now we're going to go through these
verses.
And before we do that, we're just going to
give a small break to the body.
Oh, just before we do that, I want to hear
back from y'all.
When you look at these verses,
what is the pattern that you recognize
many of them take?
What is repeated again and again,
if you know?
What is repeated?
So I heard both.
The first part of the line is repeated
very often.
And the second line...
Namaste has become like a globalized word.
Everyone knows namaste.
I want to take a moment just to talk about
it, because a lot of us may be using it,
saying it, and not even know what we're
saying.
What if namaste means you're smelly and no
one ever told you?
And it's just a big yogic joke,
because yogis have a sense of humor.
And you don't find out until you die and
go to the afterworld.
If you've never looked at the word
namaste, you don't know what it means.
The meaning, then, the joke's on you.
Words have power in every language.
So please know what you're saying to
others.
And the feelings behind words,
according to yoga psychology, and maybe
your own experience, have even more power.
So by learning the meaning, we're not only
able to say a word,
or show a gesture of respect, we're able
to send a psychic wave, which is the
actual energy of the mantra or sequence of
syllables that we're enunciating.
Somos capaces de enviar una onda psiquica,
que así es como funcionan los mantras.
Y en este sentido, el cuerpo físico es un
amplificador de la energía, la shakti más
sutil.
Namaste o nama se traduce burgamente como
saludos.
Yeah, or respect.
Many Sanskrit words don't have one literal
translation.
For example, at least in the Satyananda
Yoga tradition, what are some of the
mantras that are used the most often?
Por ejemplo, en la tradición de Satyananda
Yoga, ¿cuáles son los mantras que son más
usados con más frecuencia?
Yes, even more often.
Hari Om is used very often.
Namo Narayan is used pretty often.
And between Om Namah Shivaya and Hari Om,
what's used like very often?
Om Shanti.
And Om Shanti.
What do those three have in common?
Hari Om Tat Sat.
What does that have in common?
Put all of those four mantras.
Kung Fu, my Kung Fu grandmaster taught us
the technique that comes up the most in a
sequence of movements is the primary
teaching.
Is the primary teaching.
Everything else is the support.
Om Shanti, Hari Om.
How many different ways can we put Om?
You need to give something healthy to your
kids once in a while, right?
You put it in spaghetti.
You put it in lasagna.
You put it in peanut butter and jelly
sandwiches.
A skillful parent knows 50 ways to put
fruit in a dish.
The yogis, the rishis, the munis,
they were the parents of society.
They were social architects.
They had a vision of thousands of years
where they saw the challenges and how they
could keep us alive for as long as
possible.
Because they knew multiple times in our
evolution we will come to points where we
will almost kill ourselves.
The industrial age, including the nuclear
age, is one such example.
The new era of modern chemical-based
farming is another example.
And this era of screens, technology,
and technology is another example.
Technology and simulated intelligence is
going to present another wave of
challenge.
So a chant like this serves as a
particularly grounding reminder of where
we need to keep bringing our
consciousness.
But I went on a tangent.
We were talking about nama and this
repetition of namastasye.
And all I want to say about it now is we
really want to develop the ability to
generate feelings within us.
In Buddhism this is the practice of
bhavana or metabhavana.
Awakening loving compassion as a force.
In yoga we have pratipaksha bhavana.
Awakening the opposite feeling to a
negative feeling.
Look at the branches of yoga.
Hatha yoga is usually the starting point
for many of us.
Can you control your body and your breath?
Yeah, with a few years practice we can get
pretty good at that.
Karma yoga.
Can you manage your attitude and change
perspective?
I have to paint the whole house?
Yeah, I'm going to paint the whole house.
With a little bit of lying in the
beginning that feeling, that perspective
will shift.
Then raja yoga.
Can you keep the mind focused on one idea
for an extended length of time?
Can you hear the wind and block off the
wind, both?
Can you wake yourself up without an alarm?
Can you go to sleep on command?
Much harder.
Usually decades of practice for people.
Bhakti yoga is the fourth mastery in this
sequence.
And what is it the management of?
Emotions.
Feelings.
Imagine if I asked any of you to move this
harmonium.
Doable or not doable?
Imagine if I said there's too much sun.
Think of a solution to put some shade on
me.
Doable or not doable?
Still doable.
Now imagine I say on the beach,
prevent this wave from crashing onto the
shore.
That's bhakti yoga.
Those waves of emotion.
Every day, all the time.
Constantly shaping our personality.
Our emotions are what shape our life.
Swami Satyananda has a brilliant example
of this.
or reflection.
What is the one thing in common behind
everyone in prison?
A mismanaged emotion.
Either lack of control of an emotion or a
lack of positive channeling.
That's how significant and influential it
is in all of our lives from childhood to
the moment of death.
From the yogic perspective, it is the
final thoughts and feelings that launch
you into your next life.
From the yogic perspective, it is the
final thoughts and feelings that launch
you into your next life.
That's a pretty loaded and heavy thought.
Given how universally scary death is for
everyone.
It extremes many decades before we reach
that point of death.
But that preparation will help us every
single day.
Who doesn't benefit from remaining
relatively calm in a moment of stress or
pressure?
Who doesn't benefit from remaining
relatively calm in a moment of stress or
pressure?
When we say Namaste...
Try to see if you can connect with the
real feeling behind the word.
This was a practice of Swami Sivananda.
He said that he would mentally do Pranam
or Namaste to every living being and
person he would pass during the day.
Which for me generates a fabulous inner
visualization and feeling.
Because he was immersed in groups of
hundreds or thousands at times.
And you can imagine psychic rays of
Namaste or greeting to everyone within his
vision.
What would it be like to have that
awareness where you at least acknowledged
the humans, the dogs, the birds,
the bees that passed through your everyday
field of vision?
I know for me, and I'm not practicing
that, but when I do, it makes me feel a
lot more awake and present and connected.
So, with that, we are going to do Namaskar
Asana.
It uses the Pranamudra.
Come into a squatting position if
accessible to you, otherwise a standing
position.
Does any of that need to be translated?
Even a chair is perfectly fine.
If you're upright, then you won't be able
to spread your knees.
You could do a modified version like this.
If squatting is accessible to you,
your arms are going to be on the insides
of the knees.
If squatting is accessible to you,
your arms are going to be on the insides
of the knees.
Palms together in Pranamudra.
And as you bring the thumbs to the
sternum, the elbows push the knees out and
you look up.
Then you straighten the arms, knees close
the elbows, head comes down.
Inhaling, hands to chest, look up.
Exhaling, extend forward, head down.
Inhaling, Namaste to the sky.
Exhaling, Namaste to the earth.
Namaste to something that you appreciate
from above.
comes from below.
Namaste to something outside of you.
Namaste to something within you.
Namaste to something internal.
Namaste to someone you love.
Namaste to someone maybe you don't love.
Namaste to your body.
Namaste to your pranas.
Namaste to your mind.
Namaste to your emotions and intuition.
And Namaste to your innermost self.
Excellent.
Put the fingers under the insides of the
soles of the feet.
Take a deep breath in looking up.
Inhaling, bend forward.
Inhaling, squat down and look up.
Exhaling, straighten and bend down.
Three more times on your own.
When you finish, come back to a
comfortable sitting position.
We will begin shortly.
You can take a video at some point if you
want.
Now we are going to say Bajomana Ma,
Ma, Ma.
Ananda Mahi, Ma, Ma.
Bajomana Ma, Ma, Ma.
Satsang with Mooji
Ananda Kali Babu Ananda Mahi Babu
In the name of the Father, and of the Son,
and of the Holy Spirit.
Ananda Parivara Ananda Parivara Ananda
Parivara Bajamana Baba Bajamana Baba
Ananda Mahi Mahamandana Ananda Mahi
Mahamandana Ananda Mali Maama
Ananda Rupa Maama
Ananda Kali Maama
As the sun moves, please feel free to move
with it if you're in too much or too
little direct sunshine.
Thank you.
So hopefully you or someone near you has a
copy of the paper that has both the line
and the translation in Spanish.
It will also be done out loud,
so it's okay.
Do you guys need water?
Do you have another one for her?
Yeah, I have one.
In Spanish?
In Spanish.
So, let's try a call and repeat.
Namo Devye Mahadevye Namo Devye Mahadevye
Shivaye Satatam Namaha Shivaye Satatam
Namaha Namah Prakritye Bhadraye
Niyata Pranatasmatam
Salutations to the goddess and great
goddess.
Saludos a la diosa y a la gran diosa.
And to the auspicious ones, always
salutations.
Y para los auspiciosos, siempre saludos.
Salutations to primordial nature.
Saludos a la naturaleza primordial.
To the good one, we are ever dedicated and
prostrated to her.
Al bueno y a los que estamos dedicados,
siempre nos postramos ante ella.
So a general greeting to Devye in her most
cosmic forms.
Un saludo general para Devye en su forma
más cósmica.
Do you all have any questions about any of
those words in particular, especially
those of you who are working on your
chanting?
Si tienen alguna pregunta acerca de estas
palabras, precisamente si hay alguien que
esté trabajando en su canto, en su
pronunciación.
Rudraye namo nityaye.
Gaurye dhatre namo namaha.
Jyotsnaye chenduru pinye.
Sukhaye sattatam namaha.
To the fierce one, salutations to the
eternal one, to Gauri, to the sustainer.
Saludos a la feroz, a la eterna,
a Gauri, a la sostenedora, saludos.
To moonlight and the moon-formed one,
to happiness, salutations to you.
A la luna y a la que tiene forma de luna,
a la felicidad, siempre saludos.
So still very large qualities,
but bringing in things that are closer to
us, but not yet of the earth.
Already these verses for me are starting
to generate those waves of, okay,
we're bringing her in, remember she's this
amazing being, she's even the moonlight.
Y estamos invocando la que estamos
trayendo hacia nosotros.
Ella está en todo y estamos invocando la
forma en los rayos de la luna hacia
nosotros.
Who doesn't love moonlight?
You get the light without the sunburn.
Tenemos la luz sin que nos queme el sol.
Kalyanye pranatam vridye.
Siddye kurmo namo namah.
Nerkritye bhubhritam lakshmi.
Sarvanye te namo namah.
I mispronounced that first word,
there's no ka, it's nerkritye.
It's like an R followed by a ri.
Nerkritye.
Those types of tongue movements are very
challenging.
And the connection between the tongue and
motor and sensory cortexes is very deep.
I've worked one-on-one with mantra
chanting for stroke and Parkinson's
patients.
It's amazing what it has done for some of
their speech articulation.
Es increíble lo que han podido lograr para
la articulación del lenguaje.
Y en uno de los casos, a través del canto
en voz alta, para la corrección de la
médula espinal.
Si alguno de ustedes está familiarizado
con los saludos al sol...
Mantra chanting, el canto de los mantras,
es como practicar el saludo al sol para la
lengua.
Considerando las personas mayores que
conozcan, sabrán lo que pasa con el
lenguaje y la articulación.
Regular Sanskrit chanting of mantras will
really help keep that at bay.
Because it forces sound production from
guttural all the way to labio,
the whole range of sound possible for
humans.
To the auspicious one who increases to
those who bow.
To the accomplished one we make
salutations.
Who has the translation in Spanish?
You should have it.
No, I don't have it.
I have it.
Okay, thank you.
Because I'm inventing and I prefer to.
No.
To the southwest one, to Lakshmi of the
earth supporters.
To Sarvani, the wife of Shiva,
we salute you.
Now we also have human relative
directions.
Human relative directions.
Or cardinal directions.
You know, I read that the aboriginals of
Australia always knew where north,
east, south, west are.
That certain groups of them did not use
relative directions, no right,
left.
Only absolute directions.
This means in their working awareness they
always knew where the sun and other
celestial bodies were.
They are some of the best navigators we
know of in history.
Their brain is physiologically different
and thought to be partly because of
absolute positioning rather than relative
referencing.
When I say southwest one referring to
Lakshmi, I have a different brain.
I have to really think and do the
calculation of the setting sun.
What would it be like as an exercise just
to work on this one verse for one year and
know where the directions were anytime
someone asked you?
That would feel different.
How could it not?
Imagine a sailor or a captain that knows
where the lighthouse is versus wondering
where the lighthouse is.
To Durga, to the rescuer from
difficulties.
To the essential one, to the doer of all.
To the famous one, and likewise to the
dark one.
To the smoky one, our salutations.
I like this verse because it plants this
idea from Karma Yoga that we are not the
doer.
I don't feel that most of the time.
I'm controlling, I feel like I'm
controlling my thoughts and actions.
But then life slips out of control and I
realize, I'm reminded I actually don't
have control.
So even just verse four as a reflection
for any amount of time, the doer of all,
the rescuer of difficulties.
But not in an obvious way, she's dark,
she's smoky.
Reminding us that her manifestations
aren't always obvious.
That we might have to actually pay
attention if we want to perceive her.
To the one who is at the same time
extremely gentle and extremely loving.
extremely gentle and extremely fierce.
We bow to her, our salutations.
Salutations to the foundation of the
universe.
To the goddess, to the active one.
So with this verse, classical eastern
paradox.
She is the gentlest and she is the
fiercest.
She's the whole thing.
The entirety.
And the foundation of the universe.
And this always makes me ask in a very
honest way, what is the foundation of my
universe?
Is there any one thing that if I lost,
I would truly unravel?
Is there any one thing that would make me
lose my mind if I lost it?
For some it's how they look physically.
For some it's their mental health.
For others it's a person of which they are
so dependent that if that person
disappears, they would really have a
downfall.
What is that thing that would affect us so
much if we lost it?
Or there is no such thing.
Too abstract or real for anyone?
For you, health?
It's a question for each other,
it's not philosophical.
Some people live with cancer and no legs
and blindness at the same time.
Health is not their foundation.
One theme of the talk on the fifth day
was, everyone has to make their peace with
a disease, if they have that disease and
want to remain happily alive.
Health is a luxury and a privilege,
that not all humans have access to.
Even some of our health comes at the cost
of others' health, and that's the truth
about humanity at the current way the
world works.
Health comes at the cost of other people's
health, and that's how the world we live
in works.
Are we nourishing that which we are so
dependent on, that which is so important?
To the goddess who resides in all beings.
And is called Vishnumaya, or the illusion
of Vishnu.
Salutations to her.
And so now we've brought it down to the
plane where we live.
She's in all beings.
And she's also an illusion.
And she's an illusion.
Ya Devi Sarva Bhuteshu
Chetanitya Bhidhiyate Namastasye
Namastasye Namastasye Namo Namaha
She lives in all beings in what form?
Who resides in all beings, given the role
of consciousness.
So specifically that's how she resides
within us.
Ya Devi Sarva Bhuteshu
Some quality Rupena Samsthita
Namastasye Namastasye Namastasye Namo
Namaha Namaskar Sye Namaskar Sye Namaskar
Sye Namo Namah So now from verse 8 to 26,
we're going to follow a particular
pattern.
From verse 8 to 26, we're going to follow
a particular pattern.
Verse 8 says, who resides in us as the
form of buddhi,
intelligence.
Buddhi, the same word as buddha,
intellect, or enlightened.
The same word as buddha, which means
intellect, enlightenment.
What does intelligence mean to you?
What does it appear in your life?
In some people, it appears in the form of
studies.
Where else?
Give me something interesting.
Where does intelligence...
Problem solving, what else?
Decision making
Intuition Some people really separate
intellect and intuition.
One sec, can you translate that?
Enjoying things Some people really
separate intellect and intuition.
And it's an interesting separation if you
think they're different.
Because Manomayakosha is the domain of
intellect.
And Vijnanamayakosha is the dimension of
intuition.
But others will say the lower mind is of
Manomayakosha, simple intellect,
intelligence.
And refined intellect is Vijnanamayakosha.
Dogs have intelligence.
But why aren't they flying around in
planes?
That I'm aware of.
So there's levels of intelligence.
And someone said something else I didn't
hear.
Enjoying things?
No, viveka is discrimination.
Some people talk about the body having
intelligence.
Some people talk about the body as having
intelligence, possessing intelligence.
In our Kung Fu teachings we come to
understand that the prana has its own
intelligence.
That prana is intrinsically intelligent
and all we have to do is get out of the
way.
Traditional healing modalities come from
this perspective of don't do, rather stop
doing the wrong thing.
Nidra, sleep.
What does that mean to you?
Maybe like sleeping or you're awake?
Maybe, to me sleep means...
Sometimes it means you're awake but you're
asleep to what's happening.
I'm asking these questions very sincerely.
Because depending on our cultural
conditioning and education, sleep means
different things.
It could be like shutting off the system
and allowing it to recharge.
Yeah, and that's how we've designed
phones.
That's how we've designed phones.
I always say that if you give yourself 10%
of what you're giving your phone,
you're going to be doing pretty well.
Call it the phone sadhana.
What does airplane mode mean?
It's yoga nidra for the phone.
What is turning off the screen?
Close the eyes, because our brain takes up
more than 50% of our brain effort.
Same with the phone, as soon as you turn
off the display, you save battery power.
As soon as you turn off the display,
you save energy.
Why does this seem to reflect every aspect
of the human being?
Because we designed it.
Because humans made it.
What happens to the things we design when
we have a deeper understanding of what it
means to be human?
Our products become much deeper.
And that's why art and architecture and
sciences that come from Vijnana Mayakosha
touch different levels of humanity.
And sciences limited to the lower
intellect are often drier and more
functional.
Dryer and simpler.
Dryer.
That's a complex combination.
Hunger.
What do you hunger for?
Let's see how honest people are willing to
be in this session.
Recorded.
Will be uploaded to YouTube.
You're hungering for spirituality.
What else is someone hungering for?
Peace.
What else?
Love.
Knowledge.
What else?
Pleasure.
Peace.
Shanti.
Y'all are a very sattvic crowd.
Thank you.
Power.
What else?
Freedom.
Where do you feel hunger?
Union.
Someone feels it in their belly.
Do you feel hunger for union and peace in
your belly?
Someone feels it in their heart.
Where else do you feel hunger?
I don't know what hunger here feels like.
When I want to know something,
I feel it like...
I feel it...
It feels like the whole being wants to go
from here...
to here...
to this.
You know the essence of knowledge?
You want to take something you don't
understand, which is chaotic everywhere,
and the feeling is like...
I want it like this.
So my hunger feels different from Gita
Dhyanam's hunger.
You have to feel your hunger.
In the kosha that it's coming from.
If you can't imagine what that feels like,
you don't know what's driving you.
The hunger is real, but the direction it's
coming from is unknown.
And when that happens, we risk feeding
ourselves the wrong thing.
Sometimes we're hungry for relief from an
emotion.
And we feed it with ice cream and fries.
Mismatch of koshas.
The body gets fat, the emotion doesn't go
away.
We have to know where our hunger is coming
from.
We have to identify where our hunger is
coming from.
Another way to say this is, if we are
inviting Devi to a date,
we have to meet her at that location.
You don't ask someone out on a date and
not share the address.
That would be an interesting date,
but frustrating.
So whether she's invoking you or you're
invoking her, ask, where are we meeting?
If she's invoking you, you ask her,
where are you so I can meet you there?
If you're invoking her, you tell her where
you are and be accurate.
Have you ever shared your location on
WhatsApp?
It says accurate to 34 meters.
You can be a little less accurate,
guaranteed she'll find you.
But you have to share the location.
You know in Munger, Chaya Samadhi?
The Shadow Samadhi?
What is shadow?
What is a shadow?
A reflection.
A reflection?
Usually a lack of light, an absence of
light is usually shadow.
What else is a shadow?
Light.
It's an object that interposes between the
light and so reflects the shadow.
Something unknown of myself.
We have shadow in the physical reality.
We have shadow in the psychological
domain.
Which one is this talking about?
The mind.
What we can't see of ourselves.
Which one is this talking about?
Internal or external?
Why not both?
Why not the material world which the first
four verses said you're all of it?
Shakti is not the unmanifest,
unaccessible.
She is the manifest, the counter of Shiva.
Shakti is the manifest counterpart of
Shiva.
If we need a shadow, we can invoke her as
a shadow.
If there is a part of ourselves that keeps
eluding us, we can say I want to
understand you as me as that shadow.
Don't limit her to this or that.
That's the same as saying don't limit
yourself and your thoughts about yourself.
Don't limit yourself to yourself about
what you are or you are not.
We need to show ourselves in a particular
way in the world.
Visualize that in her, in a container and
then invoke her.
Does that make sense?
We need courage and we don't have it.
That's just a reality of life.
But what we can do is we can create a
version of ourselves, a statue.
And we say, look, I've made a statue,
now come and inhabit it.
And show me what courage looks like in a
reflection of myself.
So it's not you doing the work,
you're inviting her to live out that
version of yourself in your mind,
in your consciousness as courage and you
just watch and take notes.
And you do that again and again and again
and again until her movements,
her dance becomes familiar, until you
learn it.
And as soon as you learn it, what do you
do when you learn a dance?
You put the music on and you start to
dance.
So for me, this Suktam is basically a
recipe for how do you enter the world of
visualization in a way that changes our
psychology and manifests in our life.
For me, this Suktam represents a way of
how to enter visualization in order to
make it manifest in our life.
Generally, we give up visualization
because we think that it is so vague.
Or so impossible.
Gita Byanam was at a talk last year where
I talked about an experience in acute
depression.
I could not imagine ever being happy
again.
The life was so dark.
The idea of happy was just like... I don't
even know what that word means.
That's probably one reason I couldn't
experience it.
In that moment, I felt so bad that I
couldn't even imagine how it feels to be
happy again.
In this approach, you don't have to do
that.
You just say, Shakti, you do it.
You show me what happiness could look
like.
Until it feels familiar, which my claim
is, it will.
Giving Shakti the permission to modify
consciousness within yourself will have an
effect on the personal consciousness.
Shakti, power.
Shakti.
Say it.
Can you feel the word power in the word
Shakti?
You have to think of the word.
When I say power, what do you think of?
Energy.
What else?
Strength.
Come on, something that makes you feel it.
Sun.
Firmness.
I think bomb, like atomic bomb.
That's Shakti.
What else?
If you have to awaken that feeling.
Ocean.
Wind.
I want to hear from you.
What can you say that makes you feel the
word power?
Not in the mind, in the cells,
in the body, in the heart.
Motivation.
What is the most masculine thing you can
think of?
Arnold Schwarzenegger?
Arnold Schwarzenegger.
Who is someone with muscles that you know?
Hanuman.
Hanuman, for millions in the world.
Hanuman, you say it.
It's like Ram.
You say it.
If I think of Ram, I feel his nobility.
Because his stories are amazing.
Right?
Saying the word masculine is an idea.
Thinking of someone who embodies that is
one step closer.
Can I translate that?
Yeah.
You see how it's very easy to get stuck in
words?
To get past Manomayakosha into deep
feeling.
To get past?
Manomayakosha into deep feeling.
To really enter the waters of bhakti and
bhavana.
And I think the reason the fear is there
is because it's really powerful.
And you as an ocean culture, you all know
that better than some of us who are
landlocked.
You all have access to that every day.
That getting in the wrong way at the wrong
place at the wrong time.
And you can be sucked in to a point of no
return.
For some of us, waking up our masculinity
means we risk becoming the worst version
of a man that we've seen in our lives.
For some of us, waking up peace means we
see the worst version of passive
aggressiveness in our lives.
So with every form of consciousness,
there is that tamasic condition,
the rajasic condition and the sattvic
condition.
Those introductory verses are trying to
keep it sattvic, the auspicious one,
the great one, the helpful one.
Auspicious masculinity,
auspicious peace, auspicious power,
gentle sleep, gentle intelligence.
So it's not just the quality, it's the
color as well.
Let's get through this list.
Thirst.
Like hunger.
What do you thirst for?
Where do you feel that?
I remember once I was living in the ashram
for two years.
I had access to my guru every single day.
Then we were sent on a trip to teach
around India.
And someone played a kirtan from Swamiji.
And as soon as I heard his voice,
I felt it in my body and psyche at the
same time.
This sense of sort of drinking him.
And that's when I realized I was thirsty,
having been in his physical absence for
some time.
I was really thirsty for a more concrete
reminder of him than just a picture.
Our thirst reveals what sustains us.
You can go without food for 40 days,
that was the master fast.
The Essene people of the desert where
Jesus was around, if you could fast 40
days, you had attained a certain level of
mastery.
But thirst, much shorter.
Some say three days, some say five days.
Kshanti.
Not shanti, kshanti.
So it's like aksha without the kshanti.
That's patience.
Jati.
Species or life form.
Species, like a species of a bird.
She can come in any form.
She's not limited to just one.
I used to teach environmental science.
A western journalist came to the bush
people in Africa.
And he was supposed to meet someone to
study a tribe.
And when he arrived at the location,
a young boy was waiting for him.
No bottle, just himself.
And the journalist said, you don't have a
water bottle.
You don't have a watch on.
How did you tell the time?
And he said, I just came a few days early.
And he said, yeah, but you have no water.
We're in the middle of the desert.
How did you survive?
And the boy said, there's a water bird.
I just call it.
And then it comes and I follow it back to
water.
And at that moment, the journalist was
forced to ask himself, who is more
intelligent?
And this was the question to my high
school students, who is more intelligent,
us now or people from 2,000 years ago?
And this was the question to my high
school students, who is more intelligent,
us now or people from 2,000 years ago?
We often don't ask ourselves and we rarely
ask our children to really think about
where so much of where our current life
has come from.
Who created these solutions?
We rarely ask ourselves or our children.
Very few solutions are human solutions.
They're poor copies of nature.
We now use that scientifically in the
science of biomimicry.
And the solutions that come from that are
very rare.
far more evolved than what our limited
minds come up with.
Lajja, modesty.
Shanti, peace.
Shraddha, faith.
Kanti, beauty.
Lakshmi, prosperity.
Vritti, activity or modification.
Smriti, memory.
Daya, compassion.
Tushti, contentment.
Matri, mother.
Branti, confusion.
Indriya, senses.
This process we did with the first few
verses, I really hope you take time,
if you resonate with this chant,
to do for the remaining verses.
It's really interesting.
It never gets old, I find.
And so my final thought is, in the same
way that we do body rotation in Yoga
Nidra, you can use this rotation for
seeing where you feel and experience these
modifications of consciousness.
And just like in Yoga Nidra, if you feel
an absence or a block, that's an area to
pay attention to.
And invite Shakti into.
Please come into any position suitable for
Shantipat.
Take a few deep breaths and imagine that
each breath clears the mind of anything
you heard.
Use each breath to connect more presently
to your body.
Imagine each breath as a form of Shakti
shifting as she does.
Shakti integrating with the body,
which she also is.
Shakti extending life through that breath,
life absolutely what she is.
Imagine Shakti at the heart center or the
eyebrow center in the form of light,
a flame.
Either dancing for you or sitting still
with you.
With our awareness on her in this form,
we chant the mantra Aum to her.
Followed by Aum Shanti.
Inhale to chant the mantra Aum.
Bring
the hands into Pranamudra.
To a round of palming.
Before you lower the hands, take a few
moments to notice what you see or feel in
Chidakash.
Inhaling that warmth in through your eyes
into yourself, breathe in.
And exhaling you can lower the hands and
then open the eyes.
Hari Om Tat Sat.
Pardon me for going ten minutes over.
If you are interested in sadhanas that
work with Shakti in particular.
I hold four to five of them online.
Throughout the year they are often five to
nine days each.
They are very flexible just per what your
lifestyle allows.
They are also recorded.
And yogicapproach.com, that website will
lead you to the WhatsApp group.
And this year I am also doing a retreat in
Nepal in the village when the villagers
are planting rice.
So if you or someone you know has ever
wanted to really contact the old way that
we all came from.
And be in quite a natural environment and
just be playful with very simple people.
Then you are invited to my aunt's village.
And we will do yoga and chanting every
day.
I love going there.
There are amazing pictures of just being
covered in mud every year.
And the way the people sing together to
cover huge amounts of rice fields.
Like they are tailors of the land.
They just sow the land with seeds.
And in any case, please, in your own way,
as you might already be doing,
contact Shakti in all the ways that she is
available.
Arigatou gozaimasu.