Ariyom tatsat, to everyone.
My name is Sachidananda.
I recognize many of you and I'm happy to
see you so soon.
And for those who I'm meeting for the
first time, thank you for your interest
and support in the Yoga Vidya.
The first talk in Uruguay during this
visit was yesterday evening.
And the points that I forgot to mention,
I want to start with right now before we
formally begin the session.
One of those is thank you, Clara,
for translating.
So, as Janardhan mentioned, there are a
number of activities starting from
tomorrow.
And I happen to be one of the
facilitators, but trust me when I say I'm
not trying to promote myself.
The topic of koshas and yogic bodies and
holistic health requires immersion.
I've studied this for over 20 years,
but life changes have only happened in the
past five.
Because that's when I really had to apply
the theory.
So, you have an opportunity with the
activities planned to put yourself in an
immersive yogic setting, routine.
There are a few things I've identified
that really bring us into contact with all
five koshas.
Five layers of what it means to be human.
One of those is pilgrimages.
And all cultures have that, to go on.
Another is ashram life or monastery life,
monastic life.
Maybe you have access to that in Uruguay.
A third is an anushtan or an extended
period of austerity.
This is what shivaratri is traditionally.
Some people don't eat for 24 hours.
I know people who don't drink a drop of
water for 24 hours.
I know people who will not swallow their
sweat, their spit, for 24 hours.
They'll spit it out rather than down their
throat.
Some people choose not to sleep for 24
hours.
Some people choose not to speak except the
name of God for 24 hours.
Some people will not speak at all and will
only repeat a mantra or nothing at all for
24 hours.
And then, the fourth activity is a
curation.
An iterated retreat.
Where it's designed to systematically help
us reflect on each of these layers of
being.
So if you're not planning any austerity or
pilgrimages in the next week,
I invite you to at least attend shivaratri
or any day or the whole retreat.
And I mean that sincerely.
We can wait for life to bring us to our
knees and then figure out a survival plan.
Or we can willingly put ourselves into a
setting that deeply challenges us.
And recognize our strengths and weaknesses
in a context of positivity.
I have slowly learned to prefer the latter
and I invite you to the same.
So that's about the activities.
And a few more disclaimers from my side.
I love talking about physical well-being.
Mental health.
Consciousness and the spirit.
But I'm not a physical trainer or a
doctor.
I'm not a certified therapist or
counselor.
And I'm not many other things.
But I have dived into life and it has
pushed back against me numerous times.
And from those experiences I really like
to share what I've learned.
Not to talk about what works but to
motivate you to really experiment with
your life in a holistic way.
There are multiple experts in this room.
My guess is no one of them can solve a
problem that you have.
We have to learn to be able to read
ourselves at multiple layers.
So whatever I say is just a hint,
please put it through your common sense
filters.
If it doesn't resonate, let it go.
Don't even hold on to it for a moment.
And if something does resonate,
note it down mentally or on paper and find
a way to unpack it.
Almost 90% of the talk is taken from my
training in the Satyananda Yoga tradition.
And I pay my deepest respects to the gurus
of that tradition, Swami Niranjan who is
living and Swami Satyananda who has left.
But I'm not an official representative of
the ashram or that branch of yoga.
I'm an okay practitioner getting better.
Last thing because I know it might affect
me at some point.
There is something about Uruguay and the
heart energy.
It just opens it up for me.
It makes me sensitive.
So I already see some people tearing up
and that's going to get me super soft.
So if I need to take a breath or two,
y'all just feel free to do the same at
that time.
Any questions before we begin?
Thank you very much for those of you who
had time to fill out the feedback form.
It looks like for many of you the topic of
tonight is relatively new.
And a number of you are interested in
tools for self-reflection and life
harmony.
And for those of you who pointed out other
interests, I'm confident that there will
be something for each and every one of you
here tonight.
During one portion of the session we will
be lying down for yoga nidra.
But until that point, please arrange
yourself comfortably where you can see
without stressing your neck.
And then for the practice itself we can
come back to our mats.
We'll go ahead and begin with Shantipat.
Please bring yourself into a comfortable
sitting asana.
Any position where you can sit comfortably
still for about five minutes.
And ideally where the spine is also
comfortably upright.
Begin to make any physical adjustments you
need to bring balance to the left and
right half of the physical body.
Using the contact points between the body
and the floor as feedback into that
symmetry.
Once you create a stable base,
bring the awareness into the sit bones and
the buttocks and feel the weight
distribution on each side.
And then move the awareness up the torso
from base to top of shoulders.
Feeling for symmetry and balance in this
mid portion of the body.
Notice if there is any tension in the
shoulders or around the neck.
And see if you can suggest or allow
yourself to relax any amount.
The hands in a mudra.
A simple one is to touch thumb tip to the
index finger.
Palms up or down.
Bring the awareness into the neck and feel
that it's balanced.
Bring your attention to your neck and feel
that it's aligned with your shoulders.
Creating a natural length to the lower
spine.
And that the head is floating effortlessly
on the neck.
Eyes and mouth gently closed.
Feel into your whole sitting position as
you visualize yourself in your mind.
It's possible that impressions from the
day are moving within you.
How are you experiencing that?
Is it at the physical level somewhere in
the body?
Is it revealed in the way that you're
breathing right now?
Or maybe thoughts or memories moving
through the mind.
Or emotions or feelings still being
carried.
However the proof of your life is present
within you, be a witness to it.
Permit yourself to be that witness,
step back and just observe.
Connecting with your own breath,
begin to deepen it both directions.
So that over a number of breaths,
you're exhaling more completely and
inhaling more deeply.
Add to this deepening breath a mental
focus.
The frontal psychic passage.
An imaginary line, pathway or tube running
along the front of the torso.
It starts at the navel, moves straight up
through the sternum and ends at the throat
pit.
It starts at the navel, runs through the
sternum and terminates at the throat pit.
With the next breath in, guide breath and
awareness up this pathway.
And with the exhalation, guide breath and
awareness back down to the navel.
Continue this for a number of breaths.
If you find that the mind is not willing
to travel in a straight line, do not force
it.
With each new breath, a fresh start.
On the next inhalation, as you move up the
torso, continue all the way to the eyebrow
center.
Hold your focus at an imaginary point
between the two eyebrows, just above the
brow line.
Turn the eyes inwards, as if to look at
that point from inside.
Imagine looking at a flame which burns
steady and bright.
If the image does not readily appear,
remember a favorite candle.
Or feel free to draw the outline of that
candle.
To see the colors of a flame.
Or to feel a warmth at that point.
With our awareness on this inner light,
we'll chant the mantra OM three times
together.
Followed by the opening Shanti mantras all
If you're unfamiliar with any mantra,
simply listen and feel into the vibrations
around you.
Slow, full breath in to chant the mantra
OM.
OM OM
Om Sahana Bhavatu Sahano Bhunaktu
Sahaveeryam Karavavahe Tejas
Vinavaditamastu Ma Vindhisavahe Om Shanti
Shanti Shanti Hi
Remain with your body still and eyes
closed for a few moments longer,
and consider the intention for which you
are here this evening.
And if there is any aspect of your life
that you invite radical, positive
transformation into,
how could you form a short, positive
sentence to describe the transformation
you want?
In a way that is not dependent on external
circumstances to change,
but rather some inner quality to emerge,
develop, or evolve.
Imagine that that quality does emerge and
manifest in your being.
What would that feel like?
What would that look like?
How would you move through your day,
through your life with this new ability
and transformation?
Is this possibility imaginable,
or is it far from imaginable?
Are you able to contact the new emotions
you would experience, or is that out of
reach?
Bring your awareness to the heart center
between the sternum and the spine.
Take a few deep breaths in and out.
Imagine breathing into that point and
breathing out of that point.
And bring the hands together in
pranamudra, thumbs touching the sternum.
Rubbing the hands vigorously, generating
as much heat as you can.
And when you have something to share back
to your eyes, cover the closed eyes with
those palms.
Noticing any colors or shapes,
or maybe simply void.
And take a deep breath in through the eyes
into yourself.
And exhaling, you can slowly lower the
hands, and open the eyes.
Hari Om Tat Sat
Is that new to anyone, to do a Shantipat?
No?
Yes?
Great!
I believe that Swami Satyananda Saraswati
and the Satyananda Yoga tradition are...
are pure geniuses.
You take something that we do at the
beginning and end of every class,
that for many of us we think of it as
routine,
obligatory.
And yet, guides and teachers like him,
and other masters I've had in other
modalities,
have taught me that what you do the most
is probably the most significant.
For students of the Satyananda Yoga
tradition, the things we tend to do the
most, chant the mantra Om,
Shantipat, and repetition of Sankalpa.
A Shantipat is an entire package,
it's a sadhana.
It asks us to bring awareness into our
physical body, to observe our energetic
state, often reflected in our breath,
to be a witness of mental activity,
to be a witness of emotional presence or
feelings,
and independent of whatever storm or calm
is within,
to stabilize ourselves and complete a
process from beginning to end.
That is a sufficient life teaching,
we don't need much more yoga than that.
The issue is we have so many tools,
and very few of them are actually being
applied.
Think about any time today where you felt
stressed,
or knocked off balance, having done
Shantipat a thousand times, did anyone
today set aside three minutes to go
through it to recover?
Did anyone at a moment of imbalance
think to do Shantipat to recover that
balance?
Because we ritualize these techniques,
rather than seeing them as the tools that
they are.
I really don't want you to do with that
information that's going to come through
today.
Find ways to put the awareness into daily
life.
And I'll try and suggest some ways we can
do that.
What was the title of this talk,
Ceci?
Habitarte por completo, no?
Habitarte is...
To live in your body completely.
Ah, yes, to live fully within yourself.
As a traveler, I am blessed to be staying
in many homes.
And I have a very curious personality.
Some may say nosy.
Some may say snoopy.
Some may say, I don't know how to say
snoopy.
How do you say snoopy, Nuria?
Chismoso, yes.
So yoga is well suited for me.
Because if someone says, ah, there's this
thing called the subconscious,
I want to know how to get inside it.
And if someone says, there's this thing
called the unconscious,
and I say, well, what is it?
And they say, we can't talk about it.
No one knows about it.
It's unconscious.
Then I'll spend months trying to find the
door.
So when there's a title like live fully
within yourself,
it invites the question, well,
what am I actually?
And this is one of the original questions
that sparked the spiritual revolution.
Tens of thousands of years ago,
probably hundreds of thousands of years
ago, whatever the first being was that had
some level of self-awareness, there must
have arisen the question, what are the
boundaries of what I am?
And so we developed systems of measurement
for the material reality.
But the reality of us being humans,
we've all experienced as multidimensional.
And quite subtle as well.
And that's what makes relationships quite
challenging as humans.
We all know what love feels like.
But how do you communicate to someone how
much you love them?
We all know what pain feels like.
But how do you get someone to really
empathize with how deeply you're hurting?
Some of us have never even been given the
words to describe those measurements.
Some of us grew up in cultures where that
may never have even been explored,
much less acknowledged.
And that creates a challenging space for
those of us who want to live in a state of
peace.
Because it requires contacting these
various dimensions
and bringing some sort of harmony or
balance back into it.
And so that sets the context for us
discussing koshas.
There will be a number of Sanskrit terms
this evening, not too many.
It is a very old and very systematic
language for describing all things subtle
to gross.
Have you ever heard that Eskimos have
multiple words for snow?
And Japanese have multiple words to
describe the space under a tree.
Some cultures have ten ways to describe
the taste of pasta.
And others for the various flavors of
love.
Sanskrit, similarly, has many ways to talk
about manifest and unmanifest reality.
And a very detailed spectrum of what
humans can feel emotionally.
Psychological states.
Cognitive conditions and states.
And also other words for the energies.
And even the physical body.
So for that reason, I am happy to share
the Sanskrit language with you.
And for that reason, I will use the words
in Sanskrit, but I will always translate
them.
If you can't see, please get to a place
you can, if you want to look at the board.
We are the human and we are going to
unpack this a bit.
At a very high level, we have three
bodies.
Gross.
It couldn't be physical, but conceptually
it means gross.
How would you translate that?
Dense.
Gross.
Subtle.
And causal.
Sometimes subtle will be called astral.
I just want to spend a minute on this
because at least these two are within our
daily experience.
Our physical body is definitely in the
gross category, it's tangible.
What is an example of the subtle body?
Maybe emotions, something a little bit
more concrete.
I'm fishing.
Example.
You know what the physical body is,
everyone is clear what the physical body
is.
You move around in it, you grab,
you manipulate reality.
What is an example of a subtle body?
Visualization.
I'm sitting here, but I can take my mind
to my house in Nepal.
I can actually move around my rooms and
describe to you textures, objects.
I can tell my nephew, take this,
put it there, and when I go there
physically, can trust that my mind had
accurately described what needed to
happen.
How many of you dream?
I'm just curious who says they don't.
Everyone dreams, almost everyone dreams,
some people don't remember their dreams.
If you're in that category, that can
easily be cultivated and becomes an
important aspect when we start to contact
our whole self.
If you're in that category, that can
easily be cultivated and becomes an
important aspect when we start to contact
our whole self.
At many stages, the dream body becomes a
very effective tool.
For example, how many of you have certain
asanas that are impossible for your
physical body?
How many of you have tried to do that same
asana in your dream body?
Good.
Being able to take your sadhana into a
dream state is a milestone for working
with yoga practices.
And the experiences you have in that freer
state can be carried back into the
awakened state.
And not just for touching your toes,
you might have a boss that you find very
challenging and can't say what you need to
in real life.
But through practices like lucid dreaming
and vivid visualization,
you can repeat that scenario enough until
the nervous system is strengthened
to carry out that plan in real life.
And the astral space, the dream space,
is often a safe space to practice that.
Due to the short time we have,
I don't want to go into the causal body.
But especially for females, there are
interesting aspects.
Let me make sure I say this right.
The grandmother has already influenced egg
production of the grandchild.
The way that propagation and progeny
works, at least in human species.
The other word I don't know how to speak
in English.
Reproduction.
And that's related to the science of
epigenetics.
How our lifestyle choices now turn genes
on and off.
And how that genetic expression will
create the next wave of organs and cells
that will be passed down to our offspring
and their offspring.
And so it's a subtle but extremely
practical science for us.
To learn not only how to work with the
body that we move in every day
but the bodies that we influence that will
be walking in 20 to 30 years from now.
We all came from something.
In Vedanta, the seed
is the tree.
There's no difference.
It's just the perception of time that
gives the illusion of growth.
If you know what this seed is,
you will know what tree it will become.
For many of us, our life changes are met
with surprise.
Because we have not sufficiently contacted
and studied our seed form.
In more current psychology, this is what
the unconscious is.
Latent patterns deep within our psyche
that bubble up to the subconscious mind
and express themselves in waking life.
So it is an illusion that we're making a
lot of our choices as this conscious
active mind.
Much of that is predetermined in a dormant
or semi-dormant state.
And the better that we know or can map out
this terrain
the better we are at predicting and
navigating our own life.
And I give one short story about river
rafting in Nepal
which has some of the best and biggest
rapids in the world.
I went on a trip where there was rainfall
every day and the river level was
fluctuating.
And the river guide was able to expertly
avoid all the traps.
And I said, how did you get so good at
navigating the river especially when the
conditions are changing constantly?
He said, my team and I walk the river when
it's not changing at all
during the driest time of the year where
all the boulders and the crevices on the
river are revealed to us.
And once we memorize that whenever water
starts to flow we can predict what will
happen.
And it was a beautiful synopsis of yoga
psychology
If we develop a vision of our most subtle
self
then we are in a much better position to
handle whatever life brings to us in the
form of various raindrops.
Ok, so any questions about that?
So we get a little bit more practical now.
The Koshas are the five yogic bodies
Kosha means a sheath or a cover They are a
finer level than those three bodies we
talked about
We have the physical body everyone here is
in contact with their physical body Has
anyone ever been disembodied?
Have you ever had a state where you
couldn't feel your body or couldn't get
back into your body?
Sometimes in a room you'll have people,
people who have been in accidents,
near death experiences, emotional shock,
trauma.
Disembodiment is a great way to manage
If you don't like what's happening to your
body,
that mind has the algorithm to say,
I'm checking out until that's done.
And it can take a lot of therapy and a lot
of years to really get back into your
body.
Most of these questions are serious,
even if they sound fantastical,
because I know from experience everyone in
society has experienced things that are
traumatic.
Which word did you use?
Chromatic?
No, but the questions are very serious,
even though they sound...
Fantastical?
Fantastical.
The questions are serious, even though
they sound fantastical, because in one way
or another everyone in this society has
experienced some level of trauma.
So when you have a physical body in the
absence of anything else, when you have a
physical body in the absence of anything
else, you have a corpse, you have a lump
of meat.
Uruguayans like meat.
So I know you all can imagine what that's
like.
But let's say that there is some energy in
that lump of meat.
You can also think of it as a lump of wood
for vegetarians in the room.
How many of you are aware of your
energetic body?
Some dimension in you that changes
throughout the day or day to day.
Can you sometimes feel it in others when
someone is really energetic and it's
like...
This is why I love dogs.
Their prana maya kosha, especially
puppies, is like...
A puppy is this big, right?
He can make all of us smile.
Think about that, that something that
weighs half a kilo can lift 40 times 20,
800 muscles against gravity.
That is the power of the prana maya kosha.
That is the power of a monk that has a
strong energetic body.
That's why thousands of people visit the
Dalai Lama.
Because these beings are charged and they
will harmonize your energy body.
If you've never felt that, go to someone
who has that reputation and be in their
presence for a year.
Or get a puppy.
So what happens when you put energy in a
physical body like a corpse or a log?
What is it?
More specific example.
Yes, you get movement.
So give me an example of...
Fire is a great example.
Just because I'm going to use my examples,
fire is a great example.
You get a puppet, but because we have log
here, I'm going to say fire too.
Meaning a puppet, someone's moving that
piece of log, right?
So the first example is what happens when
you put energy in this physical body.
If it's a corpse, it could be a puppet.
And if it's a log, it could be fire.
But the puppet doesn't make decisions on
its own.
Everything is being dictated by a higher
power.
Some of us, and this is not a trial,
only live in these two bodies.
Unable to make decisions on our own,
we wait for someone to tell us what to do.
There are many cultures that insist that
some people have to stay in this state.
And you can imagine how yoga is not
welcome in certain parts of the world.
Because it implements the notion that you
have a force within you that allows you to
make your own decisions.
The modern world is familiar to you with
the mental body and the mental dimension.
To the degree of utter imbalance.
To the point of total imbalance.
I forget the author of Homo Deus.
Yes, it's him.
He writes, for the first time we have more
people killing themselves than being
killed in all the wars in the world
combined.
For the first time in history we have more
people killing themselves than being
killed in all the wars in the world
combined.
Which body do we tend to settle into?
What do you get when you add the mental
dimension to these two other systems?
I think lower than will.
You get a robot.
A robot appears that it moves according to
its will.
But it's absolutely 100% programmed.
Fully conditioned.
I can almost predict what a robot will do
if I give it a certain stimuli.
Beautiful woman, big breasts, eyes go over
there.
Guilty.
Beautiful woman, big breasts, eyes go over
there.
Aggressive person, I go backwards.
It doesn't matter what your triggers are,
I hope you are aware of them.
The more you know your conditioning,
the more emotional intelligence you will
have.
Because you can make...
Sorry, can you repeat that?
Because you can make deeper choices than
just physical environment.
I know to wear a long sleeve because
people use AC here and I get cold.
I knew to stay at home today because my
energy would be used in this talk and I
wanted to conserve.
Also simple.
From this point on, I know that I have to
stay at home.
For many of us, it tends to be a bit more
unpredictable.
What if only two of you showed up tonight?
How would that affect me?
Or there was a storm.
When I went to Australia, there was the
Bondi mass shooting.
For Australians, that was deeply shocking.
I grew up in Texas.
I've been through that 15 times in my
life.
I went to that beach the next day.
That's how life is.
So then the fourth is...
Intuitive or psychic.
How many of you...
have never had an intuitive thought?
And I want to ask because it's not always
clear what intuition is.
Anyone feel like they've never had an
intuitive thought?
A sense of knowing in the absence of any
direct evidence or logic?
Good.
What do you get when you introduce...
Well, for psychic, it includes the whole
emotional spectrum.
And I want to...
you to think of it differently than
mental, which I mean is cognitive.
And I want you to think of it differently
than mental, which I mean is cognitive.
So what would a robot with intuition be?
Yes.
Welcome, human.
In your opinion, that's what sets us apart
from a robot.
And finally, the yogis say that there is
also a causal body.
The body of vibrations.
And specifically, undifferentiated,
homogenous vibration.
From that, each new layer emerges.
We want to develop the ability to be in
contact with ideally all five of these
dimensions.
We're going to get into a practice in
about seven minutes, but at any time,
if your legs are feeling achy,
just feel free to move them around.
Very quickly, help me name some physical
systems.
Muscular.
Skeletal.
I'm going to include hormonal because it's
so powerful.
Lymphatic.
Digestive.
Great, so you get the idea.
This is partly what we're going to be
doing on day one of the retreat.
What is the physical body really from
people who know better than me the anatomy
and physiology?
If you can contact your various body
systems, you can feel into imbalance in
those systems sooner.
If you're not communicating with these
systems systematically, how do you know if
they're out of balance?
And then all of a sudden, we have knee
pain.
And then all of a sudden, our back goes
into spasm.
And then there's knots in our neck,
and we pay thousands of dollars for
massage.
Too expensive, your massage.
There's many sessions.
But it's not that the body didn't give us
signs.
That it wasn't telling us every step of
the way, Hey, something's happening here.
We are very good at ignoring signs.
It's a mental faculty, a mental strength.
Misapplied.
Okay, energetic body.
What are some of the different ways we can
check balance?
Breath.
Humor.
Too abstract for me.
I want everyone to always say what they're
thinking.
Temperature.
Nutrition.
How can you observe that in yourself?
We can measure it.
And there are some that will be in the
middle.
I'm going to put nutrition there,
because obviously it's a combination of
multiple states.
Energy level.
Self-assessed energy level.
And I'm going to fast forward this.
From a yogic perspective, you have five
pranas.
And I won't name them all for time,
but they're in different parts of the
body.
And they have different manifestations.
Hiccup.
Sneezing.
Farting.
Blinking.
Yes, I fart.
I think hopefully you do too.
I just wasn't ready.
Blinking.
All sorts of ways to diagnose the health
of these pranas.
It's a great subject to familiarize
yourself with.
What about mental systems?
Memory.
Perception.
Attention.
Memories, where do they go?
Where do they go?
Yeah, I got memory.
Let's say concentration.
That's like attention.
This can also be studied.
There are many qualities of the mind,
yogic and modern.
An important yogic one is discernment.
Sleep, where does sleep go?
Sleep spans multiple, for sure.
Definitely a lot in mental, some in
energy.
Sleep.
It's a good prediction for energy body and
of the mental body.
How many people have ever experienced
sleep issues?
That gets into the next point.
How do we use any one of these as alarms?
We want to be able to go through every
layer in each body,
every system, or subsystem, and say,
is this where it should be?
And as soon as it deviates from normal,
that should be an alarm.
If we respond to that alarm early,
it's probably easier to bring it back into
balance.
If you hit snooze 20 times,
what happens?
You get stuck in traffic.
You miss the important meeting.
You get fired.
Lose the house to the bank.
Partner divorces you.
And then you have thoughts of suicide.
This is like a normal thing that happens
in the world.
Ignore alarms, snooze on life.
Next alarm, snooze on life and self-care.
And when we finally wake up, we wake up to
a really difficult situation.
And it requires a lot of help from a lot
of different experts,
and sometimes family members and friends,
for us to come back into balance,
if we're lucky.
I've worked with a number of elderly
people, one-on-one, who are entering their
death state with things unresolved in
life.
It's hard to watch an elderly person go
with so much sadness.
You know, when you leave the amusement
park, ideally it's with a big stuffed
animal and a smile.
And yoga says it is possible, we can live
skillfully.
Enjoy most or all of our desires and leave
lightly.
Intuitive dimension.
For the moment, I just use one word,
and it's chakras.
On the ceiling there.
They are an entire map of what a human can
experience.
Fifth branch of yoga.
Kundalini or Kriya Yoga.
That's how powerful the yogis' determined
emotions and psyche are on the human life.
That an individual should first master
their body movements, then their energetic
movements, including breath, then their
mental movements, then one would be
prepared to work with emotions.
A lot of our lives, certainly mine,
is flooded with emotional,
emotional input.
I am ten times more likely to look at an
Instagram post in the morning than I am to
do my morning mantras.
Even though the effect of a single post
will have far greater implication on me,
than simply moving my wrists.
Similarly, if I chose to do the mantras
with sankalpa,
it would work for me in the positive
direction.
And that's all I'm going to write as one
of the causal systems of how to measure
it.
What is your willpower?
Read any spiritual book from any spiritual
master in any tradition.
If they were for real, they would be
talking about willpower cultivation.
Nothing happens without intention.
What created all of this?
Intention.
We want this to be.
You can't move your...
dream, imagination.
The desire.
In philosophical terms, it's called Iccha
Shakti.
The first Shakti is Iccha Shakti.
The power of desire that something come
into being.
That's sankalpa.
That's why we start everything with
sankalpa.
I know people who've trained that to the
point where even mundane actions have a
sankalpa.
It becomes deeply ingrained.
See, structure mappings.
She's not sure everyone knows what
sankalpa is.
Sankalpa is a resolve.
An affirmation.
An intention.
That has commitment behind it.
It is the vision of what you want to
manifest.
It doesn't have ideas of maybe I can,
maybe I can't.
At it's causal state, it does not even
need that.
It is a power.
It's said that someone with sufficient
willpower will be able to achieve
something.
Will say something.
And reality will bend to make it true.
These are the old teachings.
No one says that now.
People have trouble bending now.
Forget reality.
Is it a sankalpa or it depends on the
stage or the moment of life, we could be
working with other types of sankalpa?
There you can choose a deeper one yet.
Last point before practice.
Looking at sleep as something that
integrates different things.
Multiple.
Stress is one example.
Probably affecting the whole world and for
many hundreds of years.
Anything coming to y'all's minds?
Challenges y'all face that affect multiple
things.
Sleep for sure.
Sleep will help bring energy back into
balance.
If it's not happening, it will pull away,
it will bring into imbalance.
Of course that will affect the physical
functioning, the mental functioning.
That can affect intuition and emotional
management.
An interesting point about willpower.
Willpower can overcome physical
limitations.
A 12-year-old boy in Australia this week
swam hours to shore to save his family.
When they asked him how he did it,
he said, I didn't want anyone in my family
to die, I did not allow myself to stop.
Willpower can overcome energetic
limitations.
Willpower can overcome mental limitations.
And willpower can certainly overcome
emotional imbalance and limitations.
Usually the closer you get to subtle,
the more potent it is.
That's why psychic chanting of a mantra is
considered far more powerful than out loud
chanting.
And that's why, in general, repeating the
mantra mentally is far more powerful than
chanting it.
The nutrition system is also complex
because it pulls from so many different
areas.
I want to mention a topic only because it
has been coming up so much in my travels.
Many people getting separated or
relationship issues at home.
This is cross-cultural, I'm finding,
between the West and the East.
And it's on the topic of sexual
dysfunction.
And I think this was on my mind because
someone did an interview yesterday.
And Janardhan was translating.
And they were asking at the later part of
the interview about, well, what does yoga
have to offer on the topic of,
I think he said sexology.
And they asked him what yoga could offer
on the topic of sexology.
And when I use the word sex, I want you to
think about it in the most holistic way
possible.
From the power of creation, which will be
in the part of the causal body.
And in this sense, sexual energy is simply
creative energy.
I put a lot of creative energy to organize
this talk.
In yogic terms, you could call it sexual
energy because it gave birth to this talk.
And on the other end of the spectrum,
we can think of it as human sexuality,
two bodies or one body coming together.
I have been through in my life,
and I certainly meet people now who
experience sexual dysfunction,
but the way they approach it is not
systematic.
And I want you to be open to using this
for any example in your life that you
experience dysfunction or disharmony.
So let's say that a couple is no longer
comfortable interacting intimately.
The cautious system gives us a really easy
way to say, well, am I even comfortable
just touching you or being near you?
If that's a no, there's no need to get
into a dialogue about sexuality.
This dimension alone is saying,
there's a discomfort here at a very gross
level.
One of my best friends, he has a
background in massage.
And his children, age 9 and 14,
know how to ask for touch in natural,
healthy ways.
When is the last time two people ever sat
together and just harmonized or regulated
their breathing?
Or sat together in silence and just shared
the experience?
Or sat together and just experienced the
experience of seeing, feeling,
and listening together?
This is just one example in modern life
that a lot of people are experiencing
imbalance, where we can walk through the
cautious model and say, how are we feeling
here?
Or can we share an activity without having
to mix cautious?
Can we isolate ways we interact rather
than creating more complex interactions?
This is often why in a Satyananda yoga
class, you'll be introduced to movement
without any other instruction.
And then we introduce breathing with the
movement.
And then we add mental visualization and
sensory awareness with the movement and
breath.
And then awareness or witnessing of what
that triggers emotionally, if anything.
And then finally, planting the sankalpa of
what the ideal or perfect harmonious
movement would be.
And so it's very layered and systematic.
All of this, hopefully, is coming off as a
mapping system.
A mapping system for oneself.
Who are some famous people that used maps?
Or didn't use maps?
Yes, sailors.
What happened to sailors with bad maps?
We don't know.
Because they crashed or got lost.
And what happened to sailors that had
really good maps?
They expanded our view of not the world,
but the universe.
That's what we're trying to do,
isn't it, when we say inhabiting the whole
self?
We're trying to really map out what that
means and be fully present in that whole
spectrum.
This is the last thing I say about sex.
Again, not to focus on the word sex,
but rather a peak state.
Which sometimes is referred to as an
orgasm in the context of sexuality.
What does that even mean?
We know, or hopefully know, what physical
orgasm is.
What is an energetic orgasm?
What does it mean for all five pranas to
be in perfect balance, harmony,
and excitation?
What does that mean at the mental
dimension, when all sensory faculties are
on?
Receptive and non-resistant.
And merged with the object that they are
sensing.
What does that mean at the intuitive,
psychic, or emotional level, to have an
orgasm at that level?
And to experience that at the causal
level?
And to have all of that happening in all
five dimensions at the same time?
To me, that would be a very fulfilling
idea.
Complete experience.
And this is one reason, whether it's sex,
or tea, or a walk in the park,
whatever we choose to do in life,
sometimes it feels unfulfilling.
And that's usually an indication that one
or more part of us has not participated in
that process.
A misalignment of the head, the heart,
and the hands.
Okay, so with that, we go into a practice.
That was a lot of talking.
Please come to... oh, we should do one
movement.
Come into a squatting position,
unless your knees...
You're going to put your hands in between
the knees.
And as you draw the hands to the chest,
open the cup.
Exhale as you stretch forward.
Inhale as you draw back.
And do this two to three more times.
Really feel into your body, work with your
full breathing capacity.
Bringing the head forward and down will
usually stretch the spinal nerves.
The next time you reach forward,
allow the hands to separate.
Put the fingers underneath the insides of
the feet.
Inhale, look up, straightening the spine.
Exhaling, raise the hips up.
Head down.
Inhaling, raise up.
Exhaling, bending down.
Two to three more times on your own.
There's no force required.
Try and exhale out all the air in your
lungs, even if you're not participating in
the movements.
Exhale completely.
And the next time you're squatting,
release the hands.
Come onto your back, head facing me.
In the pose of Shavasana, you want the
spine to be straight.
Arms, palms up.
I would like to ask, if you really need to
leave in ten minutes, can you please raise
your hand?
It is 8.55 right now.
You have to be very honest with me because
I'm searching for boundaries now.
Okay, so no hands there.
If you need to leave in 15 minutes,
please raise your hand, be very honest.
Jeho, if you need to leave in 13 minutes,
raise your hand.
All right, I've got 13 minutes.
Janardhan's giving me, that's the absolute
max.
If you're wearing glasses, consider
removing them.
If you have anything near you,
around you, that's easily adjustable,
see if you can make that adjustment.
See yourself, imagine yourself lying on
the floor.
Observe yourself, look at yourself from
the outside in your body.
The symmetry of your legs and arms.
With respect to the midline of the body.
The balance of the head along the midline.
Take a deep breath in and feel and imagine
your body expanding.
Hold that breath in for a few seconds
until a natural tension develops.
When you feel it's right to let go,
let it flow out of you.
And allow the muscles to soften around the
bones.
As if melting to the floor.
Repeat that two more rounds.
Deep breath in and hold.
And when it's time to let go, let go of
everything.
The whole physical body with that breath.
Feel the weight of the legs on the ground.
Arms pressing into the floor.
Points of contact between back and ground.
The back of head and the ground.
Surrender the weight of the whole body to
gravity.
Aware of the plane of contact between body
and floor.
Pay attention to the stillness of the
body.
And how within that stillness there are
movements of life.
Circulation of blood.
Respiration and the breath.
You need not control any of these life
functions.
Simply be the observer, the experiencer.
Aware of the whole physical body and the
breath moving within the body.
Follow the sensation of the breath as it
comes into you.
Through the nose.
Down the throat.
Into the lungs.
And all the way back out.
Become aware of other inner sensations
such as inner sounds.
The sound of the natural breath.
The silence whenever the breath changes
directions.
Be the witness of that momentary stillness
and silence when the breath changes
directions.
The awareness will be rotated through
various parts of the body and body
systems.
Hearing it, take the awareness into that
area.
Awareness in the right hand thumb.
Index finger.
Middle finger.
Ring.
Little finger.
Palm of right hand.
Back of hand.
Wrist.
Forearm.
Elbow.
Upper arm.
Shoulder.
Armpit.
Right side of torso.
Hip.
Thigh.
Knee.
Shin.
Ankle.
Heel of right foot.
Sole.
Top of foot.
Right foot big toe.
Second toe.
Third.
Fourth.
Fifth.
Remain internally aware and listening.
Awareness in the left hand thumb.
Index finger.
Middle.
Ring.
Little finger.
Palm of left hand.
Back of hand.
Wrist.
Forearm.
Elbow.
Upper arm.
Shoulder.
Armpit.
Left side of torso.
Hip.
Thigh.
Knee.
Shin.
Ankle of left foot.
Ball.
Heel.
Sole.
Top of foot.
Left foot big toe.
Second toe.
Third.
Fourth.
Fifth.
Be aware of both legs and feet.
Any sensations within the legs and feet.
Both arms and hands.
Sensations anywhere in both arms and
hands.
The neck and head.
Imagine the blood being pumped upwards
from the heart.
The food being digested downwards.
Awareness in the mid region of the torso.
Pelvic floor.
Tail bones to pubic bone.
Area of the navel and abdomen.
The sternum and chest.
The throat pit and neck.
The eyebrow center and head.
Awareness of the whole right half of the
body.
The whole left half of the body.
Awareness of the whole body.
Full body awareness.
Including sensations within.
Take your awareness to the physical body.
A positive memory of your physical body,
a time when it felt its best.
A memory of the physical body being
challenged or diminished.
A memory of your peak energetic state in
life.
A time of diminished energy in life.
A time of mental harmony and precision.
A memory of mental fogginess or
incapacity.
A feeling or intuition that served you
well.
A feeling or intuition that was
unfortunately ignored.
Go back to the first memory you have of
life.
A positive memory in midlife.
A recent positive memory.
Connect with that part of you that is the
witness right now.
Whatever state of consciousness you may be
in.
And remaining connected to that witness,
be aware of the mind and the senses.
Use that mind to feel the breath moving in
and out.
Deepening that breath gradually but
intentionally now.
Use that expanding breath to make full
contact with your physical body.
Feel your whole body lying on the floor.
Temperature of air on the skin.
Remember exactly where you are in the time
of evening.
And slowly come out of the still state by
introducing movement.
In the fingers and toes.
Ankles and wrists.
Neck and head.
You can give your body a long stretch as
if waking up.
And exhaling hug the knees to the chest.
Walking from side to side.
And gradually coming up into a comfortable
meditative asana.
Feel free to keep the eyes closed if you
wish.
Hands in a mudra, spine comfortably
upright.
Eyes focused on the eyebrow center.
Imagine gazing within at a candle flame.
With our awareness on the idea or image of
that inner light.
We chant the mantra OM three times
together, followed by OM shanti,
shanti, shanti.
Take a slow, full breath in to chant the
mantra OM.
Slowly inhale deeply.
Shanti, shanti, shanti.
Hari Om.
Bring the hands into prana mudra.
Around the palming.
When you have warmth to share back to the
eyes, cover them.
Take a moment to notice anything you might
see or not see.
And take a deep breath into yourself.
Exhaling, lowering the hands.
Hari Om Tat Sat.
Thank you for that extra bit of time.
There are, at least, there's always extra
ideas to share.
What can I say other than I need five days
to share them?
A lot of these sharings are many years of
synthesis.
So my gratitude to you for giving an
audience to organize these thoughts that
have been collected.
We did record it and I will happily share
those.
There will be a feedback form and at the
end of the form will be a link to it.
So you can listen again if you'd like to.
And finally, I really invite you to bring
your hands into prana mudra.
Bring awareness of your koshas into daily
life.
I think many things will come through this
framework when you begin to do that.
Hari Om Tat Sat.
Thank you.
It's 9.15 for those of you who need to
leave.